<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Secret history of the Duchess of Portsmouth giving an account of the intreagues of the court during her ministry, and of the death of K.C. II.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B29600</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8231013</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204247</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264205522</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2340</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08231013</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B29600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204247)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1239:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Secret history of the Duchess of Portsmouth giving an account of the intreagues of the court during her ministry, and of the death of K.C. II.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>162 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut panel of three men standing around one man lying in bed</figDesc>
                  <figDesc>woodcut panel of two men carrying bundles and one woman carrying a small chest</figDesc>
                  <p>Is He dead</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:3"/>
            <p>THE SECRET HISTORY OF THE DUTCHESS OF <hi>Portsmouth:</hi> Giving an Account Of the Intreagues of the Court, during her Ministry. And of the Death of K. <hi>C.</hi> II.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="3-51" type="pages">
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:4"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:204247:4"/>
            <head>THE SECRET HISTORY OF THE Dutchess of <hi>Portsmouth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>FRancelia</hi> was the Daughter of a French Merchant of <hi>Iron,</hi> who having by his own Industry got a small Estate, retired with it from the Tumult and Bustle of that Great and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous City of <hi>Paris,</hi> to the Country, where he design'd to pass the rest of his Life at ease, and live on that which he had gathered together: He was not long settled in the place he had chosen for his retreat, but that being of a sociable and agreeable Humour, he got the acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and good will of his Neighbours and being withall a pretty good Companion, and one that had a little smack at Musick, he would freely drink his Glass with his Friends, and sometimes afford them some diversion with his Instruments. This ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him acceptable to all Persons of his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204247:5"/> Rank, and made him to receive Visits as well as give them to his Neighbours and Friends. His whole stock of Children consisted in two Daughters; the Eldest passably Witty and Handsome, till the Small-Pox, that implacable Enemy to all good Faces, had strangely alter'd her Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Complexion, and dull'd her Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension, so that her younger Sister, <hi>Francelia,</hi> of whom we now write the Life, was admired by all, both for her Wit, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardness and Beauty, tho yet very young, while her Sister lay unregarded, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by every one. This was the occasion of raising of some envy in the mind of the eldest Sister, who on the account of her Prerogative of Birth, did use a little more Tyrannick Power over her Sister, than otherwise she might or would have done, only to keep down her Towering Spirit, and prevent her from incroaching too far on her Prerogative; and by this means there was continually some Jarrs and Feuds betwixt the two Sisters, which were kept up on the one part by Envy, and on the other by Pride and Subtilty.</p>
            <p>These continual Quarrels betwixt the two Daughters, did not at all agree with the Fathers free and easie Temper, that made him to seek after means to make them agree, and live in that Love and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204247:5"/> Amity which should be betwixt two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons so near allied; but finding that all his labour was in vain, and that on the contrary, his Children would take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from his good Nature, to make the more disturbance in his little Family, he resolved at last to buy his Peace at any rate, tho it would not very well sute with his small Incomes, he living then at the height of his little Fortune: He propos'd therefore to his two Daughters, that seeing he could not prevail with them to live peaceably together, to have them parted, by sending one of them to a Boarding-School not far from the Neighbor-hood, and left to the choice of the Eldest, where she would accept of it, or remain with him, and he would send her Sister. The eldest Sister having refus'd the offer, thinking that in her absence the Younger would too far insinuate her self in her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Affections to her Prejudice; the Father told the Youngest, that since her Sister desired to remain at home with him, she should prepare to go; which was as readily and gladly accepted of by <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia,</hi> as it had been rejected by her Sister. In short, she went to the School, where she had occasion to shew her aptness to Learning, her Wit and Ingenuity; inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that all her Masters and Mistresses
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204247:6"/> were highly pleas'd with her, and she drew the Eyes and Admiration upon her, of every Body that went to visit their Children at that School, which gave a very great satisfrction and content to her Father, and rais'd as much Envy and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie in her Sister, in whose Ears her Praises sounded as unwelcome News, which made her to debase as much as in her lay, all those Advantages which kind Nature had bestowed upon her younger Sister: But that did not hinder <hi>Francelia</hi> from pursuing her ends, which was to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish her self as much as possibly she could, while she had this fair Opportunity, not knowing how soon she might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of it, which she fear'd would be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore she had attain'd to the knowledge of those things which she so much desir'd to learn, as being very suitable to her Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Humour: She was of a very airy brisk disposition naturally, but always allay'd with such a Portion of subtle Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy and Craftiness, which made a very agreeable mixture in her Conversation, because she would very frequently sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize People with her Repartees, which were the more taken notice of for coming from so Airy a Person, that one would have thought never gave it self time to make any Reflections nor Observations.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204247:6"/> This maturity of mind did draw the Love and Admiration of every body upon her, and some young Men began to look upon her with some sense of Passions, which she began to be sensible of, and would affect to be courted; of which the Father having been informed, he took an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion from thence to ease his Purse, in calling her home, after that she had been a considerable time at that School.</p>
            <p>She was as soon grown to maturity of Body, as she was in Mind, so that her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents finding it a business of no small diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to govern her after those Measures which they had proposed to themselves, and taken for her best Advantage, they thought of a Relation of theirs at <hi>Paris,</hi> as the fittest Person to manage her: This was propos'd by the Parents, and readily imbrac'd by the Relation, who having had some account under hand of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed Pupil, writ to have the young Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel sent to her without delay. It will be proper in this place to give you a slight account of this Gentlewoman that liv'd at <hi>Paris:</hi> She was the Relicks of a Person who had depended all his Life-time on the D. <hi>de Bellame,</hi> and who had lived al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways at the highest pitch of his Incomes; though he had no Children, he had not left so much to his Widdow, as to let her
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204247:7"/> live at ease, without keeping still in some Dependency with that Family, in which she did all she could to render her Person acceptable, and her Services agreeable to the Dutchess of <hi>Bellame,</hi> who rewarding her pains and diligence, sometimes with Presents, render'd her Life somewhat more comfortable to her. She had a good share of Wit and Industry, she was of an easie and affable Conversation, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd her not only acceptable to the Dutchess, but to the Duke also, who would sometimes please himself with passing an hour in Converse with her; neither was she so ancient, but that her Face might pass muster with such as were nor of the highest form in Nicety.</p>
            <p>It was to this Gentlewoman that <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia</hi> was intrusted by her Father, who himself brought her to <hi>Paris,</hi> and resign'd her into the Hands of his dear Kinswo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who promised him, that she would take the same care of her, in all respects, as if she was her own Child; upon which assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances the Father return'd to his Country, with all the satisfaction he could conceive.</p>
            <p>The Kinswoman having, after the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's return, well considered the Wit and Prettiness of her young Charge, she began to frame in her self some designs, which she hop'd would return in time to both their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204247:7"/> Advantages, and in order not to defer putting in execution, that which she had projected within her self, she had her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and drest after the best manner, and which most conduc'd to the setting forth of her Darlings Parts and Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. The next thing to be done, was to contrive some way to bring her to the sight of the Dutchess, as if by accident, that in case she should not approve of her insinuation into her presence, the Error should be attributed to meer Chance and Fortune, and so the more excusable.</p>
            <p>To this purpose the Matron got some body of the Dutchess's Family to give her notice, when she should next be in the <hi>Tuilleryes,</hi> that then under pretence of shewing her Niece the fine places in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> she should be walking as by accident with the young one in some part of the Garden so as to be seen by the Dutchess: This Person employed to give this notice, liv'd not far from the entering in to that famous place of <hi>Prominade</hi> and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation; and they no sooner perceiv'd the Dutchess's Coach and Livery at the Gate, but they immediately sent word to the Aunt, that the Dutchess's Coach was there, and she was not long after without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing with her pretty Niece at the same place. They passed from one walk
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204247:8"/> to another, almost all over the Garden, without meeting with the Dutchess, and at last when they were out of hopes of finding her, wondring what could be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of her, seeing her Coach was still at the Gate, they perceiv'd the Duke, who having eyed the young Niece, was drawing towards them, to learn who that young Gentlewoman was, whose face he had never seen before, which made him conclude her a Stranger. The Duke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come up to them, after he had made a Jest to the Aunt, of having made use of his Dutchess's Coach, which he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally met with empty, while he was carrying in a Chair, he turn'd himself to the Niece, to wom he made a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment, telling her amongst other things, how happy he was, to have had the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to behold a Beauty, which doubtless would be the Admiration of the whole Court. The Aunt, to save her Nieces la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and to prevent the disorders that an answer suitable to her self, and the Person had Complimented her, might cause in her, did presently reply, That her Niece was not so considerable to make ny Figure at Court, neither should she appear but very rarely abroad any where else. After she had diverted her with all the Curiosities, of <hi>Paris,</hi> which all Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204247:8"/> ar so desirous to behold, the Duke taking scarce any Notice of the Aunts discourse, did again apply himself to the Niece, saying, That she ought in Justice to appear in that same place again, to make ample reparation of all the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages which she had committed there; for her Beauty had doubtless wounded divers hearts, as well as his, in the Walk; she ought to return thither another time prepar'd with Balm, to heal those wounds she had made: That for his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, he was so much disorder'd at so surprising an Object, that he begged some immediate application of a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from her lovely Mouth; who pausing a little while, our brisk young Stranger took the opportunity to say, That she was lately come from a place where there was so little discourse of that Nature, that she was to seek what to answer; but that she hop'd her Aunt would be so kind to inform her, both as to her Behaviour and Discourse, that till then she should remain silent, chusing rather to do so, than to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at any thing that should make her pass for Ridiculous. This said with that spriteliness and brisk Air, with which she usually accompanied all her Actions, did so much please the aged Duke, that he said to the Aunt, He would take upon him,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204247:9"/> by her permission, to shew her some of the Curiosities of that City, wherefore he desired her to accompany them to the Coach, which should carry them to the Gallery of the Palace (which is like our Exchanges) where he would make her a Present. The Aunt having return'd the Duke most humble thanks for the hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our he made to them both, represented to him, that such an Action would sound too high, and might draw too many Eyes upon them which would not be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, considering her resolution to live retired with her Niece. The Duke hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing consider'd that she had reason to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline that offer, was contented with tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, them that he would send a Supper to the Aunts House, and that he would come of eat with them that Night; so taking leave of them, he went to his Coach, and fail'd not to come to the Aunts Lodgings at night, where he had before sent a very handsome Supper and Collation.</p>
            <p>It was there that the Duke wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Charm'd with the Beauty and Agreeable<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ness of his little Mistress, as he term'd her not without great admiration in the Aunt▪ at the forwardness of her brisk Niece who display'd her Wit and Parts with a subtlety far transcending her Youth. She divers times offer'd to put in a word in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204247:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:204247:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:204247:10"/> behalf of her Niece, partly to excuse her want of knowledge in the ways of the Court, and to plead the Ignorance that such young years were subject to, but she was as often interrupted by her nimble tongued Niece, who at last turn'd her Aunts Documents into a profound silence, and diligently hearkning to her discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. The Duke himself was no less ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at this young things forwardness and sharpness of Wit, and after he had staid with them a very considerable time, he took leave of his youg Mistriss, desir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the favour to please himself in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther entertainment with so agreeable a Person. Thus went the Duke, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great emotions which he found this new Object had made in his Amorous disposition.</p>
            <p>The next morning while the Aunt was busie in informing of her Niece of the ways of the Court, and of the difference which was to be us'd towards Persons of Quality as the Duke; they were told that a Person from the Duke of <hi>Bellame</hi> desired to speak with the Aunt; she pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently went to meet the Person, who told <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er that he had nothing to say to her, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hat after he had consign'd into her hands <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hat little Packet, his Commission was at <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n end; with that having delivered to her
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204247:11"/> what he had in his hand, he took his leave and went his way.</p>
            <p>The Packet consisted of two Letters, one directed to the Aunt, the other to the Niece. This last found besides a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter directed to her, a very rich Neck-lace of Pearls; after she had admired the Beauty of them, she had the Curiosity to read the Letter which was conceived in these Terms.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Know not yet whether Fortune did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend me the greatest of Pleasure, or of Affliction, when she brought me to behold those Charms which reside in your Person; you are the only Oracle that can decide that Point, according as you shall receive my small Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and my Person, the next time I give my self the Happiness to wait on you, (which must not be long deferr'd if I would live)<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> shall be able to give a guess whether you decree me for Life or Death: If you wil<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> not favour me with a sight of your Cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racters, permit your Aunt to inform me whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther I may hope a favourable Reception from you, after this free Confession; my Hear<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> commands my Hand to declare, that it n<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> longer can live, but under the Title of you<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Slave, and most passionate Lover,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>B—</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204247:11"/>
            <p>A Person so Amorous as our young Niece was, could not read such a free Declaration of Love, without feeling strange Emotions in her Soul, to be so magnificently presented, and so passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ately courted, by one of the Grandees of the Kingdom, who wanted not various Choices of Beauties, by a Person who had never seen her but the day before; all these things, besides the consideration of the great disproportion of their Ages, did put her into such Reflections, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Meditation, that notwithstanding her natural gay Humour, she could not take off her Eyes which she had fixed on the Ground, to cast them on her Aunt, who was come up to her, to give her an account of what the Duke had writ to her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Indeed, Niece, I know not what to think of you, nor of your Proceedings,</hi> said she, <hi>I am as much surpriz'd at your good Fortune, as I am at your Charms, which are irresistible, all yields to your Power, and you force even Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture her self to alter her Measures, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Effects of a youthful Spring, in the midst of Winter Snow; Be judge your self,</hi> continued she, <hi>of what I say.</hi> With that she read that Letter which the Duke had writ to her, as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:204247:12"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Must confess, that my Natural Amorous Disposition, did ever make me take all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to toy and play the Wanton with such Women, as had but such a Competency of Natures Gifts, as would invite one to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse with them; but now I find, that in sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> of Age, your Charming Niece has rais'd such Passions and Desires in me, as I us'd to feel in my younger days, at the sight of the most ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish'd Beauties; I find that nothing less than Enjoyment can lay that Storm, and quench those Flames which burn in my Breast: Let not this free Confession which I have made you, turn to my Disadvantage, and if that all the Kindness that both your late Husband and your self have received from me is not capable to gain you to act in my behalf, nor the Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of a very considerable increase of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from me for the future, perswade you to take my part, at least stand Neuter, and let me and my Fair Mistress decide the Business betwixt us. The King designs to send me out of this Kingdom, I cannot tell how soon, will oblige me to lay a close Siege, that I may have occasion to leave with you wherewith to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port my Charming young Mistriss's Expences, suitable to her Merits, and that violent Passion which she has created in the Bosom of your Friend,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>B—</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>During the reading of this Letter, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204247:12"/> Niece, notwithstanding the red colour which her tender years and unexperience in such matters, from a person of so great Quality, did raise on her Cheeks, did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a certain Joy to steal from her Heart into her Eyes, which sufficiently expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the pleasure she felt within her at the knowledge of the Duke's Passion; which was so soon perceived by the Aunt, that it hastened her to perform what she was come about, before these new Impressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons should take too much rooting in her Nieces amorous Dispsition: she therefore told her, (not regarding the loss of the Dukes Favour) These were things so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that in <hi>Paris,</hi> young, handsom Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men would somtimes receive half a dozen such Letters in a Morning, all from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons which, peradventure, they never saw nor heard of in their lives; and that these were certain set forms which were us'd by the Gallants, to exercise their Pens, and their Lackies Heels, more than their Wits and Dispositions: And that perhaps the Duke had writ the same Letter, word for word, to divers Women that very Morning. The Niece gave Ear to her Aunts Discourse, but her Heart was too much dispos'd to Love, to give Credit to what she said; she told her Aunt, She could not believe that any person should
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204247:13"/> take delight in writing such passionate things to a Woman, without feeling first some such things in their Breast; that a little time would try whether the Duke were sincere or not; and that if he should come himself after this, and make good what he had writ, it would be a great means to convince her that he dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled not. The Aunt observing by her Nieces forwardness, that the Duke's Age and Marriage conditon would be of no use to her to repel his amorous Assaults, and that she would not make any long Resistance; she found, that though her Brother-in law had acted politickly in ridding his hands of such brittle Ware, yet he had not shewed all the Prudence in the World to send a young thing of so amorous a disposition, to a place where persons were so liable to all the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons imaginable. But then, considering a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that it was a great argument of the Confidence which he had in her Virtues, that had made him to entrust his Child in her Hands; she resolved to deserve that good Opinion, in taking all the care she could possible, to keep her Niece more strict to her Duty. To this purpose she proceeded in her Instructions to her; to which she added, that she would by some means or other, make the Dutchess
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204247:13"/>
               <hi>Bellame</hi> acquainted of the Charge she had in hand (though it should prove to her prejudice) in hopes that she might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to see her; and that she made no question, but that she would so far please her, as to invite her to take her into the number of her Followers, where she would see none but virtuous Actions, and would be freed from those importunate Letters, from the Duke himself, and from all others. The Aunt was as good as her word in a short time; for after having perswaded her Niece, not without much ado, to return the Pearls to the Duke the next time he should come to see her; and to express so much Modesty in her looks and words as should deter him from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting any further; she went about what she had designed.</p>
            <p>Her Nieces arrival had made her neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, in some measure, those assiduous Attendances which she daily pay'd to the Dutchess which had made the Dutchess to inquire, Whether she was ill; and there being no body present that could give any account of her, one of her Friends came directly from the Dutchess to know the reason of her absence; that person came so luckily to serve her in her design, that she presently took the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of informing her, That a Niece of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204247:14"/> hers, whom she was willing to gratifie, in shewing her the Curiosities of <hi>Paris,</hi> as being a stranger, had caused her to be guilty of so much neglect towards the Dutchess, who she hoped would have the Bounty to forgive her, when she was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the occasion; adding, that she intreated her friend to be so kind, as to let the Dutchess know so much, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther she might without giving offence, present her Niece to her: With that she brought her Friend in, to see her Niece, whom they found sitting, leaning her Head on her Hand, which she rested on the Table, and in a very deep Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Friend, as all others, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently made sensible of this young ones Perfections, so soon as she heard her speak; and said, That she was certain the Dutchess would be so taken with her, as to retain her near her own person, and that she would be sure to give the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chess such a Character of her as would create in her a desire to see her: After that she took leave, and was going forth, when she met with the Duke, who was coming to visit his young Mistriss. The Duke being surprised at the reincounter of a Woman whom he knew was every day at his Dutchess's Toiletts, did not know well what to say for himself, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204247:14"/> being a Person of a quick Wit, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently took her by the Hand, telling her, That though he had designed, when he came, to have taken the Mistress of the House with him, to look on some things he had a mind to buy, since that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had presented him with another Assistance, he would embrace it; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently returning back to his Coach, he led the Gentlewoman along with him, of whom he dispos'd afterwards as he pleas'd, she for the present not knowing any thing of his Intentions.</p>
            <p>The Duke having rid his Hands of this troublesome Woman, he return'd a back way to see his young Mistress, whom he found all alone: Her Aunt, not thinking the Duke would give them a Visit till the Afternoon, especially, having been disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of Answers from either of them, was gone next door, to the Labour of one of her Neighbours, where she had been call'd. The Duke's coming that Morning so early, had been occasioned by the King's sending to him to let him know, he should prepare with all the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition he could, to command those Gallies and Men which he was forthwith sending to the Assistance of the <hi>Venetians</hi> in opposition to the <hi>Turks</hi> design upon <hi>Candia,</hi> this had allarm'd him, and he was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204247:15"/> come to acquaint his young Mistress with it, and to observe how she would take this News. He gave her then an account of his Business and of his Passion, to both which, the young forward one, who was not then over-aw'd with her Aunts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, gave such Answers as did suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently express how sensible she was of those signal Favours and great Honour which she had received in the Duke's Visit and Condescention, tho she had not so much Vanity, as to think there was any thing in her could invite a Person of so great Merit to speak any such things, more than by way of Diversion; and she was so taken up with the Duke's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and with what she should answer him, that she forgot at first to return the Necklace of Pearls, as her Aunt had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised her to do. But a while after, in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suance of Discourses, in which the Duke did sound her all manner of ways, she took occasion at some words, to draw it out of her Pocket, and to offer it him. The Duke surprised at that Action when he least expected it after so long a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, seeing she had not done it at first, stood a while mute, looking on her with as much love as he could express with his Eyes; at last he thus broke out: <hi>Is it possible, Fair One, that after those hopes I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204247:15"/> had entertain'd in me, I should see my self so Unfortunate, as to have the first Testimony of my Passion (tho small, I confess) so much slighted, as not thought worthy of Acceptance? Pardon me, my Lord,</hi> reply'd the Niece, <hi>that besides the knowledge of my unworthiness, I follow the Instructions of a Person unto whom my Parents have given a full Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over me.</hi> This malicious Intimation which she had on purpose made, that in performing her Aunts Advice, she might not prejudice her own Designs, and lay the whole fault on her Governess, had its wish'd for effect, for the Duke finding which way the Wind blew, he so closely ply'd his young Mistress, under the favour of her Aunts absence, that before she was return'd, he had not only perswaded her to retain the Pearls, but also to accept of what else he should send to her with such Privacy, that her Aunt, for the future, should not have occasion to disturb their Intreague with her superfluous Councils. In short, the Duke found out the way so to please his Mistress's Humour, that after some few days, in an intercourse of Letters, which were privately received from, and delivered to her, she express'd her self willing and ready to obey the Duke in whatsoever he should require of her.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:204247:16"/>
            <p>The Duke being thus got to the highest point of his Designs, thought of nothing more, but of contriving some Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for an Enjoyment. But while he had busied his Brains about that, he received an Order from the King, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him on Board within forty eight hours at farthest. This was a blow unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and though through his Advice his Mistress feigning an Indisposition, had by that means avoided being presented to the Dutchess of <hi>Bellame</hi> by her Aunt; yet he began to fear, that he should be glad to leave her in his Wives Hands, believing her more safe there from Temptations, than any where else, yet he left not endeavouring all ways ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable to come to an Enjoyment, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding his multiplicity of Business, and the small time he had to stay at <hi>Paris,</hi> but to no effect, and finding that she express'd as ready a Compliance to his Desires, as she did of Fervency in his Passions, he took the Opportunity to offer the taking of her along with him to <hi>Candia.</hi> This gave her the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to shew she had as much Courage as she had Wit and Beauty, she presently embrac'd the offer, desiring the Duke but to find out the means to take her from her Aunt unknown to her, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204247:16"/> that she should be ready at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to follow him where e're he should be pleased to command her.</p>
            <p>Her Aunt all this while, before whom she had carried her self with much more reservedness than she had at first, under pretence of her Illness, and take off all suspitions, who did not in the least dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trust any further Intriegue betwixt the Duke and her Niece, being rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to believe, that in consideration of the great disparity of Ages, he might have declin'd what he had so vigorously pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued before; being, it may be, she fancy'd, diverted by some new Object from thinking any longer on her; did all that she could to bring her Niece to that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of Health, as to enable her to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to be carried to the Dutchess in a Chair, and through her Importunities she got her Neice at last to consent to it, in lieu of giving thereby an opportunity to the Duke to take her away; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore she presently sent him word of it by their private Messenger, which was a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that taught her to Sing, which he had gained by Presents. The Duke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing advertised of that, set some Persons to watch all the Chairs that should go out of the Aunts House, with order, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204247:17"/> when they should perceive a Chair with a young Gentlewoman in it, they should order the Chairmen to follow them where the Duke had appointed that she should be received.</p>
            <p>It was not above six hours before the time given him by the King for his long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est stay, that this was done. She was carried out, only accompanied by her Aunts Foot-Boy, she being gone to the Dutchess before in a Coach to be ready to receive her Neice; presently were the Duke's Spies about the Chair, and while some were bidding the Chairmen to turn down the next corner they should come at, others were busie in amusing the Foot-Boy another way, that he should not see which way the Chair was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which they did so well, that the Boy turning his head again, and not seeing the Chair before him, he run on streight forwards, it being the way to the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ess, where he knew they had been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to carry the young Lady, still cursing the Chairmen in his heart for running so fast.</p>
            <p>Mean while <hi>Francelia</hi> was joyfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by those the Duke had appointed so to do; and they having sent him word that she was come, he staid not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204247:17"/> long after, but run into the House with all the Joy and Pleasure that the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Enjoyment could inspire him: so soon as the first Caresses and Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were over, he gave her an account of the suddenness of his departure, that he had however given order to some Persons that should supply her with all that she should have occasion, even with profusion; but that if he durst but hope, she would hearken to a Proposition which he durst not advance without her leave, and her promise that she should not take it in ill part, he should think himself the happiest Man in the World; which she having consented to, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed her going along with him in the Habit of one of his Pages, that he would be as careful and tender of her as of his own Heart; that she should have all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Accommodation, should lie in his own Cabin, eat and drink with him; that no Body should ever know of her disguise; and that when once arriv'd at <hi>Candia,</hi> it should be to her choice, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther she would continue under that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guise, or re-assume the habits of her own Sex; in fine, he told her so many fine things, and express'd so much Passion and Tenderness towards her, that she consented to all his desires.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:204247:18"/>
            <p>It was not difficult to make her pass for one of his Pages, even with his own Servants, because that two of his, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselves unfit for the Sea, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps having no inclinations to go to <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> having declin'd his Service, he was to seek for others; one he had got, which he would have made shift with, with two more that he had, so that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediately given order for a Pages habit to be ready for her; there was one got ready in the space of four hours, with which our Female Page being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couter'd, and furnish'd with all things else suitable, <hi>Capape,</hi> she suffer'd her self to be conducted by the Duke, with the rest of his Retinue, in the Admiral's Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, where she found as much Civility, Love, and Passion, as the Duke had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised she should receive.</p>
            <p>We must leave them floating on the Waves, to return to the Aunt, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long waiting for her Neice in vain, sent for her Foot-Boy, to give her an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her, and where he had lost her; the Boy said, There was such a Crowd, that he had been once intercepted by a Coach or two crossing betwixt him and the Chair; that so soon as they were passed, he had made all the haste he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204247:18"/> could to overtake it, but could not, and that he had thought the Chairmen had set down the Lady and gone their way before he came, which had made him to wait there contented.</p>
            <p>The Aunt little satisfied by this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, could not tell what to think; sometimes she fancied the Chairmen had misunderstood where they were to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry her; sometimes that some sudden Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness coming upon her, she had desired to be carried into some House, or else home again; in fine, she thought of every thing but of the right, she would have been long enough before she had thought her Neice was gone to Sea with the Duke, especially, he having given out that he was gone on Ship-board three hours before the Neice had stirred forth, that he might have time to take leave of her in private, and leave orders for all things necessary for her till his return. Wherefore the Aunt having waited long in vain, and having made all the inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries she could possible after her: in which the Dutchess her self had employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed divers of her own Servants, without success, she was forced to return home very disconsolate, where having sent for all the Friends she had, she ingag'd them
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204247:19"/> to assist her with all their Power, by endeavouring to recover her Niece, which she concluded to be stolen.</p>
            <p>The Duke having had a very quick Voyage, arriv'd at <hi>Candia,</hi> where he landed his Forces, and Intrench'd them: Some time after in an Engagement with the Enemy, a Mine Sprung under him, which blow'd him up, or so interr'd him, that from that time he was never seen nor heard of. Ill News flies fast; no sooner was that Engagement over, but the loss of so Eminent a Person was spread all over the Christians Quarters, and was carried to the Fleet also, where you may imagine how his Mistress re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented it. In an instant she found her self in the midst of Enemies, incompass'd round with Fire and Smoak, and her Ears fill'd with the Cries of Dying Men, and of others Lamenting for their Friends Losses, destitute of all Friends, Relations, and Acquaintance to protect her, in a Disguise unbecoming her Sex. In the midst of all these Tumults and Distracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, she abandon'd her self to such an Excess of Grief, that it was not probable she could have subsisted many hours longer under so great an Affliction. She was lying on a Bed in her Lords Cabin,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204247:19"/> bathed in Tears, venting of Sighs to preserve her Heart from bursting, when there came in a Gentleman, who fling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself on his Knees by the Bed-side, said, <hi>Madam, It suffices you have done your part, and have paid your Devoirs to the Memory of your Noble Friend. I share in your Affliction also, having, in the same Person, lost a worthy Friend and honourable Patron; but, Madam—</hi> At this second time that she heard the word Madam nam'd, and knowing that no Woman, but her self, was in the Fleet, she could not but start, and appear very much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, notwithstanding the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sternation she was in; and looking on that Person that spoke to her with silence, it gave the Gentleman an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of adding: <hi>Yes, Madam, as an Argument that I was privy to the Duke's greatest Concerns, I come to tell you he had confided in me the Secret of your being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd in a Pages Habit, and that he had me to promise him to assist you, in case he should miscarry; and that he would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath you to my Care and Protection; of which if you please to accept, Madam, I offer it you with all the Submission and Respect imaginable, expecting but your Orders and Commands, to act according to them.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:204247:20"/> The Damosel then found that she could no longer decline giving this obliging Gentleman an answer; wherefore, raising her self a little on the Couch, she said, <hi>I cannot, Sir, but be sensible of those obliging offers you are pleas'd to make me; and I must needs acknowledge also, that without a very great Intimacy with my Dear Duke, you could never have attain'd to so much knowledge of me, as you have express'd. But, Sir, my Sorrow is so great, and my Troubles so many, that I must, with your leave, allow to my self some longer time to allay those Disturbances, which agitate my mind; and to give a further vent to those Tears and Sighs, which otherwise would ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely destroy me: After that, Sir, I shall with humble Acknowledgments, embrace your Kindness and Assistance, in the convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of me back to my own Country. Your request is so just, Madam,</hi> reply'd the Officer, <hi>that I have nothing more to reply, but that I am from this very moment so wholly at your disposal, that you need but speak, and I shall readily act in your behalf, all that is within my Power. Mean time, Madam, I retire; but with your leave and permission, I shall leave with you a Servant that you may command as your own, and that shall know where to find me at any
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:204247:20"/> time that you shall have occasion for me.</hi> This said, he made a profound reverence, and went out of the Cabbin.</p>
            <p>Not long after, that Servant who he had left at the entry of the Cabbin, hearing our afflicted Lady fetch a deep Sigh, believing she had call'd, came in, and having demanded whether she want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any thing, she had the Curiosity to ask of him (which she thought she might do with more freedom than of others) who, and what his Master was? The Servant did readily give her satisfaction on that Point, saying, His Master was a Person of Quality, who had a consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Command in the Navy, and that he had order'd him to wait upon her till further orders: <hi>And, Sir,</hi> added he, <hi>I shall always be ready at the Cabbin door, where my Master has fixt my Post, when ever you please to call.</hi> The Lady thank'd him, and desired him to retire till she should call: The Servant gone out, she still lying on the Bed, at last she yielded to slumber, which having not got into her Eyes for some days before, did then take a full possession of her. She being thus fallen into a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Sleep, this being the third day after the News of the Dukes loss, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204247:21"/> another Officer being nominated to b<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Admiral, in order to come o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Board of the Captain's Galley, in whic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> our Lady was lying still, and tak<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> possession of his Command; he sen<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> some of his own Servants, with som<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the late Duke's (amongst which wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> two of his Pages to see the said Duke<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Goods removed) and to put in some o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> his own. They came into the Cabbi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> while she was in her dead Sleep, and by the Livery she had on, taking her to be one of the Pages, by the Strangers, who had been told by the two other Pages it was a young Gentleman, whom the Duke their late Master had taken into his Service, but just before he left <hi>France,</hi> and whom he extreamly lov'd, insomuch that none was to be admitted into his Cabbin but him, and that he doubtless had a very great Affection for his Master and had been Mourning and Lamenting for him ever since his Death; that they were glad to find him so fast asleep; and they desir'd he should not be di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sturb'd, till he awaked of himself; this made the Servants to mind their business in removing some Chests, leaving that of the Beds to another time; after which they left the Cabbin, except the eldest
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204247:21"/> Page. Thus was the young Lady left unmolested, who in the midst of her deep Sleep, her Imagination being agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated with Dreams, suitable to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to which she was reduced, made her to utter these words: <hi>Why will you be gone, my Lord, and leave your poor young Mistress behind you?</hi> This she spoke so loud and distinctly, that he who was present could not but take notice of it; and a little while after, stretching forth her Arms as if to retain him, she added: <hi>My dear Duke, I will follow you where ever you go;</hi> and with the motion she made, she awak'd, started up, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Page gazing upon her, it put her in a very great Disorder, which did but the more increase the Suspitions that her words had newly rais'd in him, of her being a Woman. The Page did presently make her sensible of the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery she had made of her self, and having compar'd divers Circumstances, during the whole Voyage and stay at <hi>Candia,</hi> with what he had heard. This the eldest of the Pages, whom the Duke had speedily design'd for some Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, had he liv'd, said, <hi>You have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd your own Secret, Madam, but let me advise you not to add more Affliction to that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204247:22"/> which has been the cause of your Discovery; and if you please to think me worthy to serve you, employ me in what you shall think fit.</hi> This he said, leaning over the Bed, with a low Voice, that none but her self might hear him from without. The young Lady being wonderfully sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd, and put into a very great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sternation, by the Discovery that the Page, or rather that she her self had made, remain'd for some time in such a Confusion, that she could not speak one word; but turning her back towards him, and covering her Face with her Hand, she put forth two or three loud Sighs, after which she said, in a low Voice, her Face being still turn'd from the Page. <hi>I know not, in the Condition I am at present, whether it be for my advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that through my Excess of Grief, you have come to the true knowledge of me; I wish that the Heavens may inspire you to contrive my return; I should not fail to give you those Acknowledgments for so great a piece of Service, as should in some measure express my Gratitude. Since I cannot longer conceal my Disguise from you, I will freely confess to you I am a Woman, a most unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Woman; but if you would have me believe that you have really any Inclinations
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204247:22"/> to serve me, confirm me in it, by not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring any further in my Concerns, nor into the Cause that brought me here, so far from my Native Country, and amongst so great a number of Armed Men, all absolute Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to me, but our late Master, who would have perform'd his Promise of returning me back to</hi> France, <hi>if it had not been his too cruel Fate to perish here.</hi> With this shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a Torrent of Tears, her sobbing stopt her Mouth, so that the Page had time, after a little pause, to assure her, that he would implicitly obey all her Commands, if she would assure him that she would but kindly accept of them; and perceiving she made no answer, but gave a free vent to her Grief, he added: <hi>I see, Madam, that your Sorrow will have its Course, wherefore I will retire, to return to you when I may be more Serviceable than at this present.</hi> With that he went out of the Cabin, telling the Servant who waited at Door, that he should not let any body come in to disturb the young Gentleman, who lay very ill on the Bed.</p>
            <p>He was just going out of the Gally, when he met with the new Commander of it, who was coming himself, with some of his Friends and his Servants, to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204247:23"/> take Possession of the Cabin, which made him to return immediately back again, believing that the young Lady might have occasion to make use of his Service, wherefore the Officer being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and perceiving one in the late Duke's Livery lying on the Bed, he inquir'd who he was; the Page made answer, That it was one of his Fellow Pages, with whom the Sea not agreeing so well as with the rest, had remain'd Sick in the Cabin; but that he would take care that he should be remov'd against Night, with all the rest of his late Masters Goods, into that Vessel which was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to go back into <hi>France</hi> with the Goods, and such of his Servants as were desirous to return. The Officer taking no further notice, after he had look'd about a little, and given order how he would have his things dispos'd, went out of the Cabin and Gally also, bidding the Page take care that it should be clear'd of all that belong'd to the late Duke, because he intended to lye there that Night. <hi>Francelia,</hi> who had heard what had been ordered, was glad to find the Page to stay behind in the Cabin, that she might consult with him, what were best to be done for the better Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealment
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204247:23"/> of her, till she was brought back again into <hi>France,</hi> where she should be in a better Condition to acknowledge his Services than there: The Excess of her Grief had already put out of her mind that other Person who had so passionately offer'd his Service to her; she look'd upon it rather as a Dream than any Reality, and was resolved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her self to rely wholly on the Cares and Services of her Fellow Page, which she believ'd she might better manage to her own mind, than any body else; she therefore turning to him, <hi>Chandore,</hi> said she, so was he nam'd, <hi>I find such a necessity of wholly trusting my self to your Care and Bounty in the sad Condition I am in, that in the Opinion I have, you are Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, and that you will deal like a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman by me; I wholly rely on your Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, only I intreat you to use all the means imaginable, with the rest of your fellow Servants, to get leave to return with all speed; for certainly it will cost me my Life, if I should remain but a Month longer in this Condition. And here is my Hand,</hi> added she, <hi>that I will be sensible of all your Kindnesses to me, when I once set foot again in my dear Country.</hi> There needed no more to spur on our brisk Page, who
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204247:24"/> having from the beginning admired <hi>Francelia</hi>'s Face, even when he believed her a Page, wishing he could get a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress with the like Beauty. He present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reiterated to her the Assurance of his Fidelity and Service, and told her, That he would immediately go and get as good a place as he could possible in the best Cabin of that Vessel appointed for their Transportation; and that so soon as he had got all things ready for her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval, he would come to fetch her, and bring along with him Persons to carry away all that did belong to her. With that he immediately went out of the Cabin, not staying for her answer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francelia</hi> somewhat satisfied with the assurances that <hi>Chandore</hi> had given her of his Care, and with the hopes of return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>France</hi> again, arose from the Bed to look after those things which did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly belong to her, in order to their removal. The Duke had been very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to her, for he entirely loved her, and at his going on that last Expedition, in which he lost his Life, he had given her a little Casket, which he bid her lock up in her own Trunk till he return'd again; but if that it was his Fate to be left behind, that she should keep it for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204247:24"/> her own use in remembrance of the Love which he bore to her. She had the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riosity to open her Trunk to look on the Casket, and peradventure, that it had gone so far as to have invited her to see what was in it, but that she had no soon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er opened her Trunck, but the Officer, who was a Marquess, and had before discovered to her his knowledge of her Sex, came in to the <hi>Cabin,</hi> which obliged her to shut her Trunk again, to receive him with Respect, his Garb, Meene, and Presence speaking him some Person of Quality, though without Attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. <hi>I am come, Madam,</hi> said he, <hi>to lead you to an Appartment which I have caused to be made ready for you, when I understood that the Commander of this Gally was to take Possion, and lie in it this Night.</hi> This convinc'd <hi>Francelia</hi> that what she had fancied to be a Vision was Reality, which made her to return the Person himself thanks for the Care he had of her; but withal told him, That the eld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of the late Duke's Pages, who design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to return to <hi>France,</hi> had taken care to get her a good Accommodation in that very Vessel which was to carry back the Duke's Goods and Servants, and that though she found her self infinitely
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204247:25"/> obliged to his care of her, yet she with his permission should rather choose to go there, that she might not be left behind, but always be in a readiness to go when they should put off to Sea. The Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer presently made answer, That to his knowledge the Gally would not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to go till they had beaten the <hi>Turks</hi> out of <hi>Candia,</hi> or utterly lost it: That to be so long confin'd to a Cabin without Conversation, and continually exposed to the Insults of Servants would needs be a very great addition to her Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, which would doubtless make her fall into some Distemper: That he had a Tent purposely for her on the Sea-Shoar, where she might be as ready at all times to embark as if she were in the Vessel; that his own Servants should continually attend her, and that she should be free from any discovery. That while the Duke was with her she might expect all manner of Civility and Respect, but now he was not, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body would be Master, that there would be such a Disorder and Confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongst his People that she could not but be very much disturb'd at it: In fine, he so well represented to her the Inconveniencies she should meet
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204247:25"/> with in the Gally, and the Services which she would receive in the Tent on Shoar, that notwithstanding she told him, That she was but waiting for <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi>'s return to have gone along with him with her Goods into that Gally. He having assured her, that <hi>Chandore</hi> should be inform'd of her removal to Shoar, by his Servant who he would leave to that purpose behind, that she consented to be led by him, and her Trunks to be carried after her by Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; designing to make an Apology to <hi>Chandore</hi> for her removal to Shoar, when next she should see him, which she be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved would be that very day: Thus was she convey'd to Shoar, and the Marquess, who had no design of letting <hi>Chandore</hi> know where he had removed her, he not liking well his own diligence, sent his Man another way, that <hi>Chandore</hi> at his coming should not be informed, but left wholly in the dark.</p>
            <p>The Officer did bring her to a very curious Tent, where were all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for her use, nay, even to Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy with Attendance, had been provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for her. So soon as she was enter'd the Tent, he having given order to all the Servants to attend without, only
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204247:26"/> leaving a young <hi>Moresco</hi> Woman with her, who had lately been made a Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, he went out himself, to give the greater liberty to his new Guest.</p>
            <p>Mean time <hi>Chandore</hi> was returned to the Gally in order to take <hi>Francelia</hi> along with him, and had brought Persons with him to carry her things; but in what Amazement was he when he found the Cabin empty both of the Lady and of all her Goods; he presently made en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after the young Page of every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that was in the Gally, but none could tell him where she was gone; they said, That an Officer of Quality had been with her, who had led her along with him into a Long-Boat, but whether they knew not; that some of their Crew were gone with them to carry her Trunks, who perhaps might give him an Account at their return: This made him to stay and wait for their coming back, that he might learn what he could from them; at their return he could get no more than that the Long-Boat had put them on Board another Gally, but they knew not its name, nor who Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it. The Officer had done this designedly, that he might not be trac'd with the Lady: So that <hi>Chandore</hi> was
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204247:26"/> forc'd to rest contented for the present, not without hopes by his indefatigable search to retrieve her again, wherefore, not to lose any time he went about it immediately.</p>
            <p>He visited all the Gallies in the Port, inquired strictly of every body in them, Whether they had not seen a handsome young Page in the late Admiral's Livery, with an Officer, come on Board them; at last, when he was almost past all Hopes, he had Intelligence, that such a one had been there, but did not stay, and that he was gone with that Officer to Shoar in the Long-Boat that had brought them thither: His next business was to get a Shoar, where he continued his diligent Search, and not knowing who was the Officer that had convey'd her to Land, he accidentally address'd himself to him, just as he was returning to her in the Tent: He with Respect inquired, Whether he could inform him of a young Page, lately belonging to the Admiral; which he did with so much earnestness and concern, that it was ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie for the Intelligent Officer, to see that it was something more than the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of a fellow Page, made him so earnestly inquisitive; wherefore, to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204247:27"/> be rid of so troublesome a Rival, he roughly answered him, That he should apply himself to other Persons to inquire after Pages, and that he did not use to concern himself with Boys: Thus went he into the Tent. This answer to an amorous Person in quest after his Hearts Desire, who being a Gentleman to of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage beyond what his youth promis'd, had doubtless provoked him to return as tart to the Officer, had he not so soon enter'd the Tent. However, as Lovers Eyes and Ears are always more open than others, he did imagine, that some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than ordinary had caused this Officer, in all other respect civil enough, to return so rough an Answer to his humble Request, this made him to hover all that Evening about that Tent, yet with that Caution, as not to be seen by the angry Officer, who he began to think had a knowledge of his Mistresses Sex, and was become his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val: He was not ignorant of the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity to which this Officer had had with the late Duke, and he believed, that the Duke, at some time or other, might have communicated so great a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to him; he knew also, what a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Command he had, and that he was a Marquess of a considerable Estate;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:204247:27"/> wherefore considering all the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which his powerful Rival had over him, join'd to the Possession of his Mistress, he thought it would be no booty for him to act in any manner but by Subtilty and Craft; wherefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved within himself, that so soon as he should certainly know the place where his Mistress was, which he did not know but might be in that Tent where the Marquess had entered, he would use all means possible to come to Speech of her, to learn from her self, whether his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices might be still acceptable to her, as she seemed to express they would be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this change; at least, so great was his Love, that if she should express any indifferency for him, or any thing to his Rivals advantage, that he would lose his Life, or rid himself of so powerful a Competitor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francelia,</hi> on her part, was thinking on <hi>Chandore,</hi> whom she lik'd well enough, and thought her self as much obliged to him as to the Marquess: She had had divers times the opportunity to observe him, he being the chief that came about the Duke, she had heard the Duke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times speak very advantageously of him, of his good Education, of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:204247:28"/> Parents, of his Courage and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress, and that he would in a very short time prefer him to an Employ suitable to his Capacity, and the Family he was Related to: This, with his readiness to serve her, and some Passion which she had observed in his Eyes towards her, did make her very much incline to favor him: She was in the heighth of those Reflections when the Marquess came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Tent. He approach'd her with an Air full of Love and Respect, but which was mixt with a certain Gaiety, with which he usually did agreeably sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son all his Actions. <hi>Well, Madam,</hi> said he, (his Passion having made him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Dress she was in) <hi>how do you like your Apartment?</hi> The word, Madam, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving raised a severe Blush over all <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia</hi>'s Face, and made her to cast her Eyes on the Ground, while she endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored to hide her disorder with her Handkerchief: It made him sensible of his Error, but it was too late to recal it; besides, he was in hopes that there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no body then in that Room, but the <hi>Moresco,</hi> whom he knew understood not <hi>French,</hi> no body had heard him from without, though he had spoken some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what loud; he came up to <hi>Francelia,</hi> and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:204247:28"/> made what Apology he could for his Error, begging her Pardon, and laying it upon the excess of a new-born Passion, which had been kindled in his Breast for her, the fault he had committed, assur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her that for the future he would be be more Circumspect. She, as unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take any notice of what he had express'd of Love, told him, She was glad there was no Person in that place that could understand him, and that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he had been heard from without, all would be well enough: She presently changed the discourse, and told him, She could not but be highly pleased with her Lodgings, for which she return'd him humble Thanks, and then said, that she wondered very much that she had not yet heard any thing from <hi>Chandore,</hi> who had promised to be with her before this; and that she had something of her own Concern to impart to him, in which he and no body else could serve her. <hi>How, Madam,</hi> replied the Marquess, in a lower tone, and with some abatement of his Gaiety, <hi>is no body capable to serve you, but that Page? Does he know so much of your Concerns, as to have so much power to serve you? I thought my self the only happy Man,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:204247:29"/> Continued he, <hi>who knew of your disguise, and—</hi> he was going on, when <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia,</hi> to break off his further inquiry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that business, said, <hi>Sir, he was my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Page, and in that respect he might have so much knowledge of my Affairs, as to be serviceable to me, though he should not have any knowledge of my Sex. It is concerning some Papers, Sir,</hi> continued she, <hi>that I would discourse him, which I cannot find, and that peradventure he might give me some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation of them: If I was but assured they were in the Fire, or in the bottom of the Sea, I should be as well satisfied as if I had them: I know not whether in my late disorders I might not scatter them, and he have lighted upon them.</hi> The Marquess, who had all this while narrowly obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her, did fancy that he had perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed some change, more than once, in in her Countenance, during her Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, he took no farther notice of it, but designed to watch so narrowly <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi>'s steps, that he should not have the opportunity of seeing her once, much less to speak to her: He therefore in his turn turned off the Discourse, giving her an Account of the posture of Affairs, reserving for after Supper, to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:204247:29"/> speak to her of his Passion; but a Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage being brought to him that a Body of <hi>Turks</hi> were advancing towards the Head Quarters; and that it was order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he should forthwith, with his Battalion, go to maintain a Pass which lay in the way. It obliged him to quit <hi>Francelia,</hi> though not without expressing some regret for it, and giving orders that his Supper should be brought to the young Gentleman, and that all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants which he left behind, should give their Attendance to him, as to his own Person. The orders were so pressing, that he had no more time but just to take his leave of her, and to tell her, That he feared not but to have good Success, if she did but favor his Actions with her good Wishes: With that he got on Horse-back to join his Battalion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="51-110" type="pages">
            <p>
               <hi>Chandore,</hi> who had been hovering about the Tent in a grey Campagn Coat, to disguise himself a little, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing seen the Marquess take Horse, came to the Tent Door, and there he so well insinuated himself with the Servants, that at last he got Intelligence from one, who had over-heard the Marquess to say, <hi>Madam.</hi> He gave him some Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stols,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:204247:30"/> which caused him to shut his Fist so soon as he had felt them, and to open his Mouth, saying, That of truth there was a Person within that Tent, which had a Livery on, and that he verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved he was nothing less, than what he seemed to be; that through the great Respect the Marquess shewed him, the Services which he had ordered all his Servants to render him, and his once calling him, <hi>Madam,</hi> not to mention the Beauty of his Face, he verily believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that it was some Gentlewoman, which he had met by chance, conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under the habit of a Page.</p>
            <p>This discovery, as it highly pleased <hi>Chandore</hi> on the the one hand, did very much perplex him on the other, to find that his Mistress was so well known; he persuaded that Servant to step aside with him a little, because he had some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Consequence to communicate to him; the Fellow complied with his Desires, and having got him to a Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlers, there he told him, That of truth it was a Woman, and his Sister, that the Marquess had got, and that he had some things of great moment to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to her, that if he could but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:204247:30"/> bring him to the speech of her, or at least convey it into her hands a Letter, which he would deliver to him, assuring him that he should be very grateful to him: The Servant made answer, That as he was but one of the Inferior Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and not admitted to come into that Tent, he believed it impossible for him to perform, but that there was a <hi>Moresco</hi> Woman, which the Marquess had placed with the Gentleman, that he would endeavor to put the Letter into her hands, and make the best signs he could to get her to deliver it to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. That if the <hi>Moresco</hi> took the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from him, he would peep through some hole to see whether she delivered it, and would give him an account of it. <hi>Chandore</hi> had been also informed by this Servant, that the Marquess had given a strict Charge, that no Person should be admitted to the sight, or speech of her; wherefore he dispaired of obtaining that Happiness, till he had first informed her that he was thereabouts, ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her Commands, being prohited the sight of her, by her Goaler, (thus he termed the Marquess) having writ a Letter to that purpose, he gave it the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:204247:31"/> Servant, who promised to deliver it to the <hi>Maresco</hi> Woman, and to bring him an answer where he was, if he could get one. Thus he left <hi>Chandore</hi> at the Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlers, and went to try what he could do; After some time waiting at the Tent Door for some conveniency of delivery without being seen, he at last contriv'd this way, he turned his Back towards the entry, and holding the Letter in his hands behind him, thrusting it into the Door of the Tent, he moved it up and down, that notice should be taken of it, which had its effect; for at that very time <hi>Francelia</hi> reflecting on the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on she was in, and fearing that she could not deal so well, and come off so easily from the Marquess's Courtship, which she found she could not affect, as she might do of <hi>Chandore</hi>'s, if he opposed her desires: She was wishing that she might see him, and perceiving a Paper to wag up and down, she fancied there might be some Mystery in it, and peradventure that it might be from <hi>Chandore;</hi> she had reason to believe that the Marquess had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd her in his Promise, of letting <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi> know where she was, because she ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believ'd, that if he had had any Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:204247:31"/> of it, he had doubtless been with her before that; she therefore went to that part of the Tent, and unseen to the <hi>Moresco,</hi> snatch'd the Paper, which a little while after she read; It was as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It may be dangerous to say more at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, than that I have had a World of Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties to find you out, your Goaler, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis, is infinitely Jealous of you; I had the ill Fortune to ask of him after you; he gave me a scurvy answer: This Servant I have gain'd, did hear him call you Madam; you pass with him for my Sister: Take what measures you can from these Informations, to let me know, by the same Person, in what manner I may serve you with my Life.</hi> She having read this, drew a Pencil, with which, on the back part of the Letter, she writ these few Lines. <hi>I have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to believe all you have writ to be true, and I am also inclin'd to believe you intend me well, and that you would serve me; I find here too much of respect and Services, as of Jealousie also to be well pleas'd; come to my Tent in the Morning, and I shall endeavour to let you know what advice this Night shall give me.</hi> She having clos'd this Note, and perceiving the Hand to wag, as if it crav'd an
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:204247:32"/> Answer, she went towards it, and put the Note into it, the <hi>Moresco</hi> Woman not observing it, which was presently convey'd to <hi>Chandore,</hi> who was impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently waiting for it: He rewarded the Servant, and desired him to continue his Friendship to him, in case he should have further occasion for it; which being promis'd him, he went to pass the Night as well as the Impatiency he was in to see his Mistress, would permit him.</p>
            <p>In the Morning early he got to the Tent, he was walking the Rounds about it, when <hi>Francelia</hi> appear'd at the Door. He soon spy'd her, and coming up, he told her softly, That he was ready to obey her Commands. Though the Servants were displeas'd at <hi>Chandore</hi>'s discoursing with her, they durst not express any dislike, for it was none of their fault; if there was any design in it, it was of their own contriving, and they had no order to hinder her from taking the Air at the entry of the Tent, as she had pretended to do, no more than to prevent her in any other of her Actions and Desires. She told <hi>Chandore,</hi> She fancy'd she should be more contented to be in the Cabin he had
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:204247:32"/> provided for her in the Galley, than where she was, because she fear'd, that in time the Marquiss's imperious Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our might be very uneasie to her, and that she hop'd he would be more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaisant to her in any way, though she was highly respected by the Marquiss, but with such an Air, that gave her cause to suspect she could not expect the continuation of it long. <hi>Chandore</hi> proffer'd to lead her away instantly, but did not know how to get her Goods remov'd. They were plotting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving together what to do, walking in the Shade aside of the Tent, when the Marquiss came Galloping up, and surpriz'd them together.</p>
            <p>He had at some distance perceiv'd <hi>Francelia,</hi> which had made him set Spurs to his Horse, but had not discern'd who that Person was that spoke to her, but he no sooner did alight but knew it was <hi>Chandore;</hi> yet making as if he had not taken notice of him, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress'd himself to <hi>Francelia,</hi> whom taking by the Hand, he led into the Tent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chandore</hi> being thus again depriv'd of his Mistress, when he was busied with her in contriving to get off, by her own
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:204247:33"/> consent, remain'd as if he had been struck with a Clap of Thunder, his Love and his Courage did suggest to him divers bold Enterprises, but fearing still, that if he should use main force, it would redound more to <hi>Francelia</hi>'s Prejudice than to his Advantage; after divers Fluctuations of Mind, he chose rather to continue to gain by Subtilty, though with longer time, that which would be much more hazardous by open force, he retired therefore with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to make further use of that Person whom he had employed before with so good Success.</p>
            <p>The Marquiss, mean time, having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained <hi>Francelia</hi> with the Success of that Expedition he had been employed about, without the least taking notice of his having perceived <hi>Chandore,</hi> she thought fit to conceal from him the knowledge of her seeing of him, in the Opinion, that he had not been disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, seeing he had not made the least mention of him. Thus did they both dissemble and conceal their different Thoughts and Designs, under pretence of other Discourses. But the Marquiss was no sooner shifted in his own Tent,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:204247:33"/> but that he went about ordering of things, so that <hi>Chandore</hi> should no longer be a Thorn in his Side. He went to the Commander in Chief, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to him, That there were divers of the late Admiral's Retinue that lay idle, which might render signal Service, and he particularly insisted on a certain Page of the late Dukes, to whom he said, the Duke had designed to give an Employment in the Army; that as a Friend to the late Duke, he intreated him to put him upon some Expedition, in order, immediately after his return from thence with Success, to give him the first Vacancy.</p>
            <p>This was so well relished by the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, who was both willing to gratifie the Marquiss, and to do something in Honour to the Memory of the Duke, that he immediately sent for <hi>Chandore,</hi> and commanded him to act next and immediately under the Chief Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of those Forces which he was send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth that night, to surprise and force a Pass from the Enemy. Poor <hi>Chandore,</hi> astonished at the Command, which at any other time he had been ravished to have obeyed, durst not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse the Honour that was made him,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:204247:34"/> though by it he was forced to leave <hi>Francelia</hi> in the Power of his Rival, and not have the time and opportunity of delivering her from it, as she had seemed to desire, nor to take his leave of her; and the General ordering that Horse and Arms should be delivered to him, with all things necessary for that Expedition, out of his particular Store, (which was a singular Favour) and to immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair at the Rendezvous of that Party; all that he could do, was to return the General Thanks, and to obey his Orders without delay.</p>
            <p>Thus did the Marquiss rid himself in an honourable way, of those Inquietudes which this young Rival gave him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out letting him know that the blow came from his Hand.</p>
            <p>The Affairs of the Christians grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daily to a Ruine, as fast as the Turks gained Advantages over them, being over-run with the vast number which he powered into that Island, from all the Parts and Dependencies of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire. The French bethought themselves of a timely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, and every Officer perceiving that the next Assault the Infidels should give unto the City of <hi>Cana,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:204247:34"/> would be likely in all Reason to carry it; they began every one in particular to contrive for their own Safety. Our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quess, who had a considerable Estate to invite him to live to enjoy it, and who came first into <hi>Candia</hi> but as a Voluntier, was none of the last to provide for his Safety, being the more induc'd to be one of the forwardest on the account of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia,</hi> whom he passionately lov'd.</p>
            <p>For this reason the Marquess made choice of that Vessel appointed for the Transportation of the late Duke's Goods and Retinue, it being ready fitted to put to Sea for his Carriage, and in a short time after, having had Intelligence, that that Party which the General had sent, in which <hi>Chandore</hi> was ingag'd, had been totally defeated; and that the Turks pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su'd their Victory so close, and prov'd Conquerors in all places they went; and that already there were divers French Officers Embark'd, in order to return; he of his own Power and Authority caus'd that said Galley to put out to Sea, where he and <hi>Francelia,</hi> with all their Goods and Servants being Embark'd, they were the first that came to the French-Coast.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Francelia</hi> return'd into her own Country, not without having daily
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:204247:35"/> been sollicited by the Marquess, to obtain the same Favour which the Duke of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lame</hi> had enjoy'd. Whether he succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Addresses to her, I am not able to determine, my Memoires failing me in that particular, yet it may easily be guess'd, that she who was so forward to accept of the Duke's offers to transport her to <hi>Candia,</hi> was no less willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow the same Favours upon a Person that took the care of her in her return to <hi>France.</hi> The Marquess was no sooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to <hi>Paris;</hi> but divers of the first Rank desir'd to be inform'd of him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the most remarkable Passages that had hapned in <hi>Candia,</hi> and amongst other things, having once mention'd to a Friend of his, the Rencounter he had with <hi>Francelia,</hi> after the Death of the Duke of <hi>Bellame,</hi> whom he had taken along with him from <hi>Paris.</hi> This Friend related it to another, and he to a third, by which means it came to the Princess <hi>Dorabella</hi>'s Ears; and she was extream desirous to learn the Adventure of that young Damsel from her own Mouth.</p>
            <p>She having found her Aunt dead at her return, had taken (or the Marquess for her) a handsom Lodging, where she still continued to receive the Marquess's Visits; and pass'd some moments also
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:204247:35"/> in contriving what excuse to give the World for her Ramble to <hi>Candia.</hi> She thought none more fit, than to say, That while, to her great content, her Aunt was making means to admit her into the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chess of <hi>Bellame</hi>'s Retinue, the Duke, her Husband, had accidentally had a view of her, and had caus'd her to be forcibly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Marseilles,</hi> where he had put her on Board, and carry'd her away to <hi>Candia,</hi> much against her Will, and all the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications that she could make to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. With this formal Story she went at <hi>Dorabella</hi>'s Command to wait upon her, who was so taken with her feign'd Innocence, and the witty account she gave of her self, and of the Duke of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lame,</hi> which she illustrated as she did think fit to her advantage, that what with that her gay Humour, and the pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiness of her Person, she was highly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ress'd by <hi>Dorabella,</hi> and receiv'd into her Family.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dorabella</hi> had not entertain'd <hi>Francelia</hi> very long in her Service, when that <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannides</hi> judg'd it very necessary, for the Advancement of his Affairs, to send her to prevail with her Brother, a Prince of the Isles, to enter into a private League with him, both Offensive and Defensive, notwithstanding a Tripple
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:204247:36"/> League which had not long before been made betwixt the said Prince and others. And <hi>Tyrannides</hi> having had the satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hearing and admiring the Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Francelia,</hi> he thought her not only fit to accompany <hi>Dorabella</hi> into the Isles, but also judg'd her a proper Instrument to forward his Designs on the Isles, and to influence wholly the Prince and the chiefest Ministers of his Councils: She was therefore pitch'd upon to be one of the Princesses Attendance to the Isles; and not only as a bare Cypher, but as one proper to manage, with good Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, any business of State that should be committed to her charge: It is certain, that her sound Judgment, accurate Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension; her happy Memory, her smart Wit, and insinuating Way was sufficient to Captivate the Mind of so Amorous a Prince as was the Prince of the Isles, especially, when all those Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishments were accompany'd with some share of Beauty and Love, though but in an outward appearance.</p>
            <p>The Princess <hi>Dorabella,</hi> who was very glad at this occasion of going to the Isles, that she might have the opportunity to see once more her Brother, the Prince; made all the diligence possible to leave <hi>Paris:</hi> In short, she came safe over the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:204247:36"/> Seas with a magnificent Train, where the Prince her Brother went to meet her. She soon, by all her Charms, so won the Prince, that he quite forgot the Tripple League, to enter into a new Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance with <hi>Tyrannides,</hi> more strict than ever had yet been, the Articles of which Treatise were Signed, and presently ratify'd by the two Princes But this was not all, <hi>Francelia,</hi> who had acted but an indifferent part in the procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this new Alliance, according to those Instructions she had receiv'd, was to manage things of much greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences yet, though that of breaking the Tripple League and making a new one appear'd to be a Master-stroke. <hi>Francelia</hi>'s Cunning and Subtilty, which she conceal'd under a serious Air, did in a short time insinuate very far in the Prince's Mind; insomuch, that when <hi>Dorabella</hi> was to return, he shew'd and express'd no less reluctancy in parting with <hi>Francelia,</hi> as he did with the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, and had as much forgot his former Mistress <hi>Cornelia</hi> as he had the Trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple League; his whole Thoughts being for the present bent on <hi>Francelia. Dora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella</hi> knew very well the Prince her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's natural Propensity to Love, and how apt he was to take Fire, that made
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:204247:37"/> her to press her return, to blow up still more and more those Flames which <hi>Francelia</hi> had kindled in the Prince's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som; wherefore she would, in the Prince his presence, frequently bid <hi>Francelia</hi> to prepare for returning; and as oft as she repeated those harsh sounds in the Prince's Ears, he would feel a great disturbance in his Mind. <hi>Francelia</hi> also, who could not but observe the Prince's new-born Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards her, would tyrannize, and frequently mention the desires she had of returning; insomuch, that at last the good Prince, not able to contain any longer, broke out into this Passion, <hi>Would to Heaven, Madam,</hi> said he to his Sister, <hi>that you were sensible of the trouble which I feel at the parting with you, you could not for pity but retard your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for some days longer. Dorabella,</hi> glad that the Prince had broke the Ice, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, That she found, the longer she stay'd the more sensible she should be at the Separation from a Person so dear to her as he was; wherefore, since there was a necessity of parting, she thought the sooner were the better to avoid the greater trouble by a less. <hi>I am sensible, Madam,</hi> reply'd the Prince, <hi>of the hard necessity of losing you, and seeing it is una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable, be pleas'd to grant me one hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:204247:37"/> Request, that I shall make to you before you go, in order to allay the anguish of my Heart for the loss of your dear presence. Is there any thing within my Power,</hi> reply'd the Princess, <hi>that I can refuse you?</hi> The Prince answering with a profound Bow, said, <hi>You cannot but be sensible, Madam, that you have lately found I could refuse you nothing, that emboldens me to go on with my Request, which is, you would be pleas'd to leave a Jewel of yours behind you in my Custody, and under my Charge; assuring you, that I shall be as careful of it, as of the Apple of my Eye. You needed but to name, to succeed in such a trifle, Sir,</hi> reply'd <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabella,</hi> who guess'd well enough at the nature of the Jewel; <hi>Is it any I have about me, Sir,</hi> continued she, <hi>or any other that I have worn since I came here? Go fetch,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded she, speaking to <hi>Francelia, the rest of my Jewels, that the Prince may chuse what he pleases. It is here already,</hi> said the Prince, and taking <hi>Francelia</hi> by the Hand, as she was going out, <hi>this is the Jewel which I demand of you, and which I prize above all those that adorn you.</hi> The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess was highly pleas'd as well as <hi>France<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> that the Prince run so readily in the Net that was spread for him; told him, That she was extreamly sorry she could not for the present grant him his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:204247:38"/> because she had promis'd <hi>France<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>'s Relations to bring her safe back to them, but that she would endeavour to prevail with them to let her come again, to have the honour to be made Maid of Honour to the Princess, and that she would so soon as she came to <hi>Paris</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, so far oblige the Prince, as to write a Letter to the Princess, to beg the favour of her to receive <hi>Francelia</hi> in that Quality, which if she accepted of, then should <hi>Francelia</hi> be immediately sent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the Isles again.</p>
            <p>The Prince was forc'd to have patience, and to be contented with this Assurance, not doubting but that the Princess's good Nature would easily be wrought upon; and truly he feared much more <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s high Spirit and jealous Temper, than any opposition from the Princess.</p>
            <p>The reason of the Princess's not yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Francelia</hi>'s remaining in the Isles at that time, was, that she might punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally follow those Orders which had been given her, which was, first to try the Prince's Inclinations towards <hi>Francelia,</hi> and if certain to take effect according to their desires, then to bring her back to receive such further Instructions, and to be instructed with such Secrets, which there was no occasion otherwise to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>close to her.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:204247:38"/>
            <p>The Princess <hi>Dorabella</hi> having now compleated all that was in her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, and not before, she was impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to return, to give so good an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her Negotiation as she was able to do; and the Prince over-joy'd at the Promises he had obtain'd from his Sister, was not so earnest, as before, to retain her longer. <hi>Dorabella</hi> return'd then, with all the outward Expressions of Sorrow, for parting with so dear a Brother, but with a real excess of inward Joy at her good Success; and the Prince return'd with those that attended him.</p>
            <p>Amongst the Grandees that had fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the Prince, <hi>Villarius</hi> was the most magnificent, and who had the most knowledg of all that the Prince had transacted, either private or openly. He was at that time so much in the Prince's Favour, that the Prince thought sit to tell him, he would have him to keep se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret what he had heard or seen, of what Nature soever, especially of his new A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, from the knowledg of <hi>Cornelia,</hi> whose high Spirit and jealous Humour he apprehended above all things. <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> did in part observe what the Prince required of him; but his hatred to <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> was such, that he could not conceal from her knowledg the Prince's new
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:204247:39"/> Mistress, which he let her understand by a third hand, with hopes that it would even break her proud Heart.</p>
            <p>This Feud betwixt those two eminent Favourites, was of that Consequence, that it is convenient I should give the Reader some knowledg of it; because that in the pursuance of <hi>Francelia</hi>'s Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, those two Persons are very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably concern'd.</p>
            <p>Not long before the Prince of the Isles return'd from his Exile, the springing Beauty of a young Lady did make such a noise all over the Kingdom, that <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> who was related to her, grew very impatient to see her. It is well known that he was the most accomplish'd Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the World, in all respects of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, insomuch that he seldom tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but he overcame; and all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests being gain'd at a very easy rate, he made so little value of them, that Love, whom he had so often offended, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd at last to revenge herself for all his Inconstancy towards the fair Sex, by the means of this his Kinswoman's Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Villarius</hi> being related to that Family, as I have said, he took that advantage to give a Visit to his Kinswoman, the young Lady, who then liv'd with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:204247:39"/> of hers; there he was received as a near Relation, but his great Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this Charming young Lady, did soon put into the head of this Relation, that <hi>Villarius</hi> did not afford them the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Presence, on the bare account of a Visit. <hi>Villarius,</hi> when he saw that Beauty, was charm'd with her, and at this very first enterview, he did tell her all that so passionate an Heart as his was could express, of tenderness to so amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Person. She affected to seem as if she understood not Loves Dialect, and that did but the more inflame <hi>Villarius</hi>'s desires.</p>
            <p>He was not long, by his frequent Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sits, before he made her to confess, she was improv'd under his Tuition; and that she began to answer pertinently to her Master's Interrogatories, yet not so subtily, but that her Governnant had such warning given her, that she thereupon hastned a Match, which had been some time in hand, betwixt that young Beauty, and a Gentleman of a very good Estate: In short, the Matrimony was Consummated, notwithstanding all the secret Oppositions that <hi>Villarius</hi> could make against it. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he left not his pursuits for that, tho he acted not so openly as before; and she answer'd so obligingly all his Expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Love, that he made no doubt but
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:204247:40"/> to come to Enjoyment, so soon as any fair Opportunity should offer it self; and he had some reason to believe this, by the Assurances that she had given him, of the Love she had for so accomplish'd a Person.</p>
            <p>Things were at this pass, when the full Resolutions were taken to bring the Exil'd Prince of the Isles in again, which was soon after accomplish'd, to the great Joy and Content of the whole <hi>Nation.</hi> Amongst those Ladies that long'd for the Honour to kiss that Prince's Hands, our young mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Lady was not the least Solicitous. She received that Honour, not as the rest of the Ladies did, but with an opinion, that when the Prince saluted her, (as he did the rest of the Ladies) she had obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved something in his Eyes, and felt some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from his Lips, which she fancied he had not express'd to others; and from that time she entertain'd such Thoughts in her Mind, as were very suitable to her Ambition. She began to fancy, that to be beloved by a Prince, was an Honour as far beyond that she could receive from <hi>Villarius,</hi> as that was above that of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sipid dull Animal, call'd an Husband. She grew Melancholly upon it, and Sick also, which made <hi>Villarius</hi> to double his Visits; but he still found an entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:204247:40"/> which did daily grow colder and colder; yet he had so good an opinion of himself, that he did wholly attribute it to her Indisposition of Body, which was really a Distraction of Mind. In a word, though the Lady did in time reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as to her bodily Distemper, she still seem'd to be in an anxiety of Mind, which set <hi>Villarius</hi>'s Wits to work to find out the cause, but without Success.</p>
            <p>At last <hi>Villarius</hi>'s Visits grew so uneasy to her, that she had not the Power to conceal any longer, she did not find in them that Delight and Satisfaction which she formerly had done: though she was far from telling him so much, yet her Actions spoke so plainly the Change Ambition had wrought in her Mind and Inclinations, that <hi>Villarius</hi> could not but be as fully inform'd of it, as if she had spoken it to him, in as plain Language as ever she uttered in her Life. The most apprehensive <hi>Villarius</hi> presently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood her, which made him to say, <hi>What is there in my Conduct, Madam, of late, that may have produced so strange an alteration in you, as you manifest in your Actions, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all the Care and Circumspection with which you manage your self?</hi> She sigh'd, and readily answer'd, That she had nothing to alledg against his Conduct, and that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:204247:41"/> if he found any Alteration in her, he was to attribute it to some Relicks of her late Distemper, which peradventure did render her something more shagrine than usually, which he ought to bear with. <hi>Yes, Madam, I believe you,</hi> reply'd <hi>Villarius, and I am very apt also to judg right of the cause of your Illness; Love, Love is the Author of my Misfortune, and I am the more to be pitied, because I am left in the dark, as to the Object of your new Affections. My Lord,</hi> answered she again, <hi>I here declare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Heaven, that I know no Person in the World, for whom I have a greater Inclination, than for your self. Yes, Madam,</hi> reply'd <hi>Villarius, but no Love, you had not else so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten deferr'd and put off from time to time those Favours, which you have been pleas'd to own my constant Passion did deserve. I find, Madam, that you reserv'd them for some more happy Rival, while I must still languish, and be fed with vain Hopes and empty Promises. Well, my Lord,</hi> replied <hi>Cornelia, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess to you, that you have a Rival, but after so fair a Confession, do me so much Justice as to believe that this your Rival is not so in point of Love: No, my Lord, it is in Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you are rival'd, as a mark of my Love to you; I have brought my self to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, that my Ambition prevails above my Love, and that it will be the first serv'd and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:204247:41"/> satisfied. In a word, my Lord, this last Passion is so powerful in my Mind, that nothing less than a crown'd Head can allay it. I must be belov'd by the Prince, I must be the Prince's Mistress, or I must die in Dispair.</hi> At this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration <hi>Villarius</hi> stood motionless like a Statue, which gave her time to add: <hi>I must allow of your Surprizal, my Lord, but believe that my discovering of this Secret to you, is the greatest mark of my Love, that I could possibly confer upon you, till by your means and assistance I am entertain'd by the Prince, which is the only way to satisfy my Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, after which I faithfully promise to reward your Affection and Services, with my last of Favours, and to consent to whatsoever you shall please to desire from me:</hi> And finding that <hi>Villarius</hi> remained still mute: <hi>Remember, my Lord, that the Prince is not properly your Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val; and, by Heavens, you need to fear no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: It is my Ambition only that he must sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy, but you my Love; only Ambition will be first serv'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Villarius</hi> looking still stedfastly on her, after he had fetch'd a deep Sigh, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered: <hi>Certainly, Madam, your thoughts of me are very singular, and you must needs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me the most passionate and constant Lover, or a Man of the most easy temper in the World, to be work'd upon. Well, Madam, you shall find I am both; but you must judg
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:204247:42"/> of my easiness to yield to such strange and sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Propositions, as you have made to me, by the excess of my Passion towards you. Yes, Madam, I will use that Power I have with the Prince, to satiate your Ambition; but deceive me not, Madam, after that, neither defer one moment longer, to satisfy my Passion; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, I must tell you, Madam, that you will raise such another Passion in me, that all your Charms would never have Power to allay, and that would transform your best of Friends into an implacable Enemy. I go, Madam, to work your ends with the Prince, as you desire, that I may, without further delay, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain what my Passion has so long languish'd for.</hi> With saying this, <hi>Villarius</hi> went out, and in a short time he so wrought <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>'s Interest with the Prince, whom he found very much inclining that way, that <hi>Cornelia</hi> said she had no more to do, but to reward <hi>Villarius</hi> according to his Merits and her Promises. But she, who upon the Favours which she had newly receiv'd from the Prince, through <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi>'s Mediation, had let her still growing Ambition stifle her Love; in lieu of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying him, as she had promis'd, did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that shun all the opportunities of see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him; which being perceived by the slighted <hi>Villarius,</hi> and that all he could do would not so much as get her to discourse
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:204247:42"/> with him, nor so much as answer any of his Letters, he turn'd that great passion of Love he had for her, into as great an one of Hatred and Revenge, though not without a great Conflict, in which at last Revenge prevail'd. Thus that Lady, to obtain great Titles, did sacrifice to her high Spirit and Ambition, the most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Lover that she had ever had, which will in some measure justify <hi>Villarius</hi>'s se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity towards her, of which we shall have occasion to treat some particulars in this Discourse, so far as they relate to our <hi>Francelia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Princess <hi>Dorabella</hi> being returned to <hi>Paris,</hi> and having given <hi>Tyrannides</hi> a full and satisfactory account of her Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Francelia</hi> was presently taken to task; she was intrusted with the Court-Secrets, and fully instructed in the part she was to act, both with the Prince of the Isles, and with those State-Ministers and Courtiers, that were become Pensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners to <hi>Tyrannides</hi>'s Mercenaries. <hi>Dora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella</hi> was also advis'd to write immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to the Princess of the Isles concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Francelia,</hi> that the Prince's Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards her might not cool. <hi>Villari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> was also solicited to decline the Interest of <hi>Cornelia,</hi> and wholly to espouse that of <hi>Francelia,</hi> which being altogether ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:204247:43"/> to his own Inclinations, he most earnestly imbrac'd, and did as vigorously pursue.</p>
            <p>The Death of <hi>Dorabella,</hi> which for the Suddenness and Nature of it, surpriz'd all the World, following presently after, and a Letter coming from the Princess of the Isles to have <hi>Francelia</hi> sent to be one of her Maids of Honour, notwithstanding all the Arts that <hi>Cornelia</hi> used to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. <hi>Francelia</hi> was put into the Hands of a Person of Quality, who took care to conduct her over into the Isles, and to resign her into her Majesty's Hands: There were private Lodgings got for her at first, till others were prepared for her in the Court. The Prince failed not to visit her so soon as she came, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press all the Passion imaginable towards her; but all this he did with the greatest Privacy imaginable, for fear of raising such a storm in <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s Breast against him, which he should not be able to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Yet was she inform'd of it by <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi>'s means, who hop'd it would tear her Heart in pieces. The Prince continued so assiduous in his private Visits to <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia,</hi> it began to be suspected he had some Inclinations that way, and from divers Hands did <hi>Cornelia</hi> receive the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful News of her Rival's getting
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:204247:43"/> ground upon her; mean time the Prince was very diligent also in visiting <hi>Cornelia,</hi> to take all Suspicions from her: But that would not do, she was too subtile and too much concern'd, to calmly suffer a Stranger to intrench upon her Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. She was the Prince's first Mistress, since his return to the Isles; nay, his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Mistress, on whom he had bestow'd vast Sums of Money, and the highest De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Honour, and she would not calmly yield all those Advantages to a <hi>French</hi>-Woman, of neither Birth nor Fortune, beyond what she had got by her Services. This caus'd <hi>Cornelia</hi> to set Spies upon the Prince's Actions, that should bring her word when the Prince should go next to see her Rival, that she might intercept him, and take him to her self. It was not long before News was brought to <hi>Cornelia,</hi> that the Prince was to sup with <hi>Francelia</hi> at her Lodings, with <hi>Villarius;</hi> she presently gave orders that a very great Supper and Banquet should be prepar'd against such an hour that Night, and getting into a Coach, she ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd up and down near <hi>Francelia</hi>'s Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, just about that time she had been inform'd the Prince was to go thither in a Hackney Coach: At last she was told that the Prince was in that Coach which
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:204247:44"/> she saw coming towards her; she present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caus'd her Coach-man to turn about, and so she met the Prince full-butt; she told him she was just going to invite him to come and sup with her that Night; that she design'd to surprize him, which was the reason she had not given him a solemn Invitation; then she wondered at his being so private in a Hackney, ask'd him where he was then going? that it made her fear he had some private Assig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: to all which the fond Prince made no other Answer, than that he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Frollick to be merry with half a dozen Persons, which he was told were got together, in whose Company he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much delighted; and finding that <hi>Cornelia</hi> made no mention of <hi>Francelia,</hi> he did all he could to divert her from any such thought, by beginning a Discourse of quite another nature, and by freely getting into <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s Coach out of his, so went along with her, you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine with what Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelia</hi> did treat him the best she could, and made him to pledg her so frequently, that at last he had quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got his other Appointment, and began to be as merry and well pleas'd, as if he had had no other design than that he was about. In short, <hi>Cornelia</hi> did so flatter him, that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:204247:44"/> he lay there all that Night, and it was late the next Morning before he depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Mean time <hi>Villarius</hi> and <hi>Francelia</hi> had been presently inform'd of the trick which had been play'd the Prince, so that so soon as they heard that <hi>Cornelia</hi> had seiz'd on him, they had given up all hopes of seeing him that Night, they supp'd together: <hi>Villarius</hi> gave <hi>Francelia</hi> divers Assurances of his humble Services, and that he would highly revenge that Affront which <hi>Cornelia</hi> had put upon them; and they both concerted together, which way to return to her some Trouble of the same nature. <hi>Villarius</hi> told <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia,</hi> That he had been lately inform'd that <hi>Cornelia</hi> had had some private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with a certain person, whom he would cause to be watch'd, and that he doubted not, but he should, by the means of his Spies, surprize them together; that if so, the Prince should have the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to catch his Rival with her. <hi>Villarius,</hi> in fine, told so many fine things to <hi>Francelia,</hi> and gave her that Night such Assurances of his Friendship and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that she remain'd very well satisfied with him.</p>
            <p>She had been inform'd of the Prince's Humour to a tittle; amongst the rest,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:204247:45"/> that the more a Woman pretended to Vertue and Chastity, the more was the Prince's Heart inflam'd towards such a Person, she resolv'd therefore to appear very reserv'd to the Prince, and never to allow him any Favours, but with the greatest Reluctancy imaginable; and she did carry her self after that towards him with so much seeming Modesty and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that she pass'd in the fond Prince's Thoughts for a very Angel.</p>
            <p>The Prince was no sooner got to his Palace again, and retired for some Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but that <hi>Villarius</hi> came to him with a smiling Countenance; the Prince told him presently, as a great Secret, how he had been met by <hi>Cornelia,</hi> who had taken him to Supper with her, and that for fear she should have any Distrust of him, he had condescended to her Desires, and lay'n there all Night. <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> to let him know that he was not so secret in that business as he imagin'd, told him what they had for Supper, and some of their private Discourse: at which the Prince seemed as much surprized as could possibly be. <hi>Sir,</hi> said <hi>Villarius</hi> to him, <hi>To let you know that I am informed of all</hi> Cornelia<hi>'s Actions, I shall e're long let you see how faithful she is to you, and what reason you have to be so to her, and to stand
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:204247:45"/> so much in awe of her as you do. I know one of her private Friends, Sir,</hi> continued he, <hi>and I shall be punctually inform'd of their next time and place of meeting, and it shall be your fault if you surprize them not toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The Prince, who was unwilling to believe any such thing of her without good Proof, yet glad if he could have such an opportunity to convince her of her Treachery towards him, whereby to take down her high Spirit, did not know whether he had best to thank <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> for his offer, and to accept of it, yet at last he said, That certainly, if she was so false to him, he should have just cause to slight her, and more publickly own his Love to <hi>Francelia,</hi> whom he thought to be very vertuous, and that he feared he should have much to do to gain the point; that he did not dislike her for it: On the contrary, it made him but the more earnest to obtain that which she was so tender of, and so unwilling to part with, he verily believing she was a pure Virgin. <hi>Villarius</hi> having inform'd him in his Opinion, so soon as he left the Prince, who bid him go and make an Apology for him to <hi>Francelia;</hi> he went to her, and told her all that the Prince had said concerning her, and let her know how necessary it was for her
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:204247:46"/> to carry on the same Humour of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty and Vertue, with which she had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready so well prepossessed her princely Lover.</p>
            <p>The Prince, who had not seen <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia</hi> in three days, thought the time ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long, and notwithstanding his fair Promises to <hi>Cornelia,</hi> to remain constant to her, he went privately to see her that Night. She who had been very free and pleasant with <hi>Villarius</hi> but the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, did put on her feigned Modesty, and so inflamed the Prince with it, that he protested he had never met with a Humour so agreeable to his as was hers, and that he languish'd for her. <hi>Sir,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Francelia, the Honour which you are pleas'd to do me, is infinitely above my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; and I am sorry, Sir,</hi> continued she, <hi>that I have nothing to return to you for it, but my Prayers to Heaven for the Prosperity of your Grace; all that I can do more, is to wish it were in my power to do more.</hi> This said with a languishing Air, and a dying ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and with Eyes, which though full of Fire, were fix'd on the Floor, did so charm the good Prince, that he answer'd, <hi>I wish, Madam, you would take the pains to consult with your self a little, and reflect, whether you have not besides your good Wishes, something else at your own disposal, that you
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:204247:46"/> might bestow on me, for that great and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Passion I feel in my Bosom towards you. Peradventure,</hi> continued the Prince, <hi>that some other might be more happy than me, though not more in love with your Charms, and that you would repay their Love with Love, and return your Heart for theirs. There is no Person in the World, Great Sir,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Francelia, that can set a greater va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and esteem on your Vertues and Bounties than I do; and it is certainly the greatest of my Troubles, that I am destitute of means to express more effectually than with words, what I feel in my Bosom towards so much Perfection as you ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> master of. These are still but Wishes, Madam, and you certainly are Mistress of far greater Treasures,</hi> answer'd the Prince; <hi>you have a Heart, Madam, to bestow, because I have been credibly inform'd that you have never ingag'd it yet; would I had wherewith to purchase such a Treasure. If Love could do it, I dare boast of deserving it, beyond all the World. You have but too much Worth, Sir,</hi> reply'd she, <hi>to purchase so mean a thing; if any thing could gain a Heart but in exchange of another, no other price, Sir, can buy that Merchandise. If that were all,</hi> reply'd the Prince, <hi>were I Master of a thousand Hearts, they should all be laid at your Feet in exchange of yours; mean time, be pleas'd, most charming</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:204247:47"/>
               <hi>to accept of my single Heart, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of yours, with all the Love and Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that your Perfections have kindled in it. I can but desire and wish, Sir,</hi> replied <hi>France<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, that I had Merits sufficient to deserve suc<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> an Honour, if it were in your Power, Grea<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Sir, to bestow it once more: you know, Sir, how often like a Lover you have bestow'd i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> upon another Person, with whom I might dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pute it, as to Esteem, Respect, and eve<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Love to your Excellency; if you had not en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gag'd it farther, since even past all Redemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, but by Death. That is it, Sir, tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> makes me say, you have not wherewith t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> purchase an Heart, and that I can have no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing but my best Wishes and Prayers for you besides that general Esteem that all who kno<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> you have for your Perfections.</hi> The Princ<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> was so strangely surpriz'd at this unex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pected time, that he was very glad <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius</hi> came in to break off the Discours<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> for the present, and give him time t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> consider of what he should say to so cun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning a Mistress as he had now to d<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> withal. <hi>Villarius</hi> came to tell the Prince that that very Night he would shew him some sport.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francelia</hi> had been receiv'd a pretty while since into the Princesses Retinue, and had Possession of her Lodgings a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Court, notwithstanding all the Intrigue<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:204247:47"/> and Plots which <hi>Cornelia</hi> had made to defeat her. The Prince therefore had not far to go to visit her at any time. <hi>Cornelia</hi> had appointed to meet her new Gallant in her own Lodgings that very Night, where he was to pass to her Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces; he told the Prince of this, and assur'd him, That if he would go and surprize them in the dead of the Night, he should certainly find them together. The Prince, whose Bosom was new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inflam'd with Passion towards the charming <hi>Francelia,</hi> assur'd him, That he would for never so much lose so fair an opportunity of detecting <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Amours, that he might have just cause to break off with her, and wholly turn all his Affection on his new charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mistress. So the Prince retir'd with <hi>Villarius,</hi> telling <hi>Francelia,</hi> That he would leave to another time what he had fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to say to her; and he went away to prepare himself for the night Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelia</hi> had cast her Ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ng Gentleman, who made a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Figure at Court, and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Meen, Youth, and Vigour, was very much according to her Relish. The Prince's Distractions in his Amours, did not permit him to give her all that Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:204247:48"/> which she us'd to receive from him, and which her Constitution requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. She had therefore taken the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to let this Person know that he was to her Mind, and that it was his own fault if he were not happy; and that Commerce had lasted so long, that it began to be whisper'd abroad; but she did not much value that, because it made for her purpose, both in creating some small Jealousy in the Prince to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite him the closer to her, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the more her great Enemy <hi>Villari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Cornelia</hi> and her Lover for more Freedom, and better Conveniency, had concluded the Enjoyment of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in her own Appartment, where all the Servants were at her sole disposal, and would be all very secret. The Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant was come, and they had plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feasted in a private Appartment, where none but the Servants of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret were at any time admitted to enter; and from thence there was a private C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s Bed-Chamber: so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ald the Prince come at any tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ugh he had free access, and that all Doors were continually open to him, yet the Lover might with ease e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scape from his knowledg, except the Prince should surprize them in Bed, at
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:204247:48"/> the dead time of the Night, which was not likely to be, without it were upon some intelligence, and with design. About midnight the two Lovers went to Bed, and presently after, by the removing of some things, the change of Servants Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the retirement of others, that Servant who <hi>Villarius</hi> had gain'd, and who was his faithful Spie, gave notice, that now it was time for the Prince to come. The Prince came accompanied to the Door of <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s Lodgings by <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius;</hi> he went in, and thence directly enter'd <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s Chamber, where he found them both in Bed together, the one lying in the others Arms, yet with such Circumstances, and the effects of such a present Wit as had <hi>Cornelia,</hi> that the Prince was absolutely deluded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelia</hi> had no sooner been inform'd by that Woman who was upon the Watch in the Anti-Chamber, that she heard some Body coming up Stairs, and had heard the Gates open; but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the Proverb, <hi>'Tis good to be sure,</hi> she pull'd off at once her Night-Cloaths, which hung all together, and clap'd them on her Lover's Head just when she heard her Chamber-Door to open with that Key the Prince usually kept, which opened all passages to him: She fell to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:204247:49"/> groan and complain, as if she was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ill. The Prince ran pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently to her Bed-side, and seeing <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> in a Woman's Arms, and she making sad complaints, he would not draw the Curtain more open, for fear the Light that was on the Table should offend the sick <hi>Cornelia,</hi> but stooping down, <hi>What is the matter with you, Madam,</hi> said the good Prince. <hi>Oh! dear Sir, is it you,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered she, <hi>how glad am I you are here? Good Sir, do so much as hold my Head which is ready to split in pieces, while this Gentlewoman runs to my Closet for something for me. I'le go my self,</hi> reply'd the Prince, <hi>tell me but what I shall fetch? No, pray Sir,</hi> reply'd <hi>Cornelia, you know not where to find it, pray give her leave to go: Come, I'll hold the Prince's Head in my Arms,</hi> continued she, <hi>while you get out of Bed, he shall not see you, do not fear it.</hi> The Prince, who thought it was the Gentlewoman's Modesty that requir'd that Ceremony from him; free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let <hi>Cornelia</hi> blind him while the Gallant slip'd out of Bed, and went to the Woman Sentinel to bid her run into the Closet, and fetch any Glass out from thence, to amuse the Prince with, while he should dress himself and make his escape.</p>
            <p>Mean time <hi>Cornelia</hi> kept the Prince in Discourse; sometimes crying out of her
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:204247:49"/> Head, and desiring him to hold it gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; she told him, That having had some small symptoms the last Night, present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after Supper, of this violent Fit, she had desir'd that young Gentlewoman, who had supp'd with her, to lie with her also that she might talk with her if she could not sleep, and to be serviceable in case she grew worse of her Head, that her Distemper had so increased, that she had been forc'd to pull off all her Head-Cloaths, and to toss and tumble about for ease; that she was just slumbering a little in the Gentlewoman's Arms when his Highness came; and that she was so overjoyed at his coming, that she thought she was something more at ease than she had been, and believ'd she should sleep if his Highness would but lie down, and let her lay her Head in his Bosom; to which the Prince presently yielded. By this time the Woman was come with the Bottle of Cordial, and holding <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s Night-Cloaths behind her, which the Gallant had given her, she made as if she had taken them up near the Bed-side, she gave the Cordial to <hi>Cornelia,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired the Prince to take some, which he did. She sent the Woman for fresh Night-Cloaths, but the Prince, who was mightily concerned in himself, for
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:204247:50"/> having so easily given credit to what had been so falsly reported of her, and at her illness, was mov'd with so much tender Compassions towards her, that he would not by any means permit her to put on fresh Linen, but said, that those she wore before, would do very well, and that he would be contented with them, so he made haste to undress him, that he might go to Bed to his dear afflicted Mistress, and to afford her all the Assistance and Comfort he could possible, by way of Compensation for the wrong he had done her in his Thoughts, fully resolv'd to tell <hi>Villarius</hi> his own, and never more to believe so slightly on false Reports.</p>
            <p>Mean time the Gallant was fled, glad that he had come off so clear, from so eminent a Danger, thinking he should never praise and admire enough the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Wit, and ingenious Contrivance of <hi>Cornelia,</hi> who he doubted not after that but would lull the Prince asleep in those Arms which he had been freed from, much against his Will. <hi>Villarius,</hi> on the other hand, wondering that the Prince stay'd so long, that he heard no noise in the House, nor saw any Lights, did not know what to think; he had the Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity to hearken at a low Window, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:204247:50"/> while he was listning he saw the Gate open, and a Man run out like Lightning, insomuch, that <hi>Villarius,</hi> who at first had a design to stop and examine him, soon lost that thought, the Person being so suddenly got out of sight, and out of hearing, by the favour of the Night: That made <hi>Villarius</hi> conclude rightly, that the Prince had miss'd of the Prey, and that <hi>Cornelia</hi> had so well inveagl'd and allur'd him, that he would pass the Night with her; and not doubting but that Person who had run out of the House so hastily, was the Gallant, he a little while after retir'd, vex'd that the Prince had lost so fair an opportunity of discovering <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s falseness to him, and himself of giving <hi>Francelia</hi> the next Morning a pleasant account of that night's Discoveries, but not without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of out-witting <hi>Cornelia</hi> at some other time. Thus did <hi>Villarius</hi> leave the Prince in the Arms of that Person he had lov'd, but now hated most, not without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising to himself yet a full and entire Revenge, when the next opportunity should present it self.</p>
            <p>The next Morning, when news was brought him that the Prince was in his own Appartment, he came to him, and the Prince receiv'd him with such a cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:204247:51"/> that express'd what were his Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and how much he thought he had wrong'd him in putting him on such Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travigancies; and scandalising a Person whom he lov'd, to gratify his particular Revenge. <hi>Villarius</hi> amaz'd at the Prince's Expressions, said no more, but only begg'd his Highnesses Pardon, and told him, That it was none of his fault, if after he had lodg'd the Dear, he had been so blinded as not to see him, and to let him go. <hi>Let who go?</hi> reply'd the Prince, <hi>I rush'd into</hi> Cornelia<hi>'s Room e're it was possible she could have any notice of me, and I found her in her Bed, her Heir dishevel'd, almost di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted with a cruel Head-ach, and no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the Room but a Gentlewoman that assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her. That was the Man, Sir, you were to have seiz'd, and who having escap'd your Hands, got away from me also afterwards, through the favour of the Night, and the nimbleness of his Feet. Do you think I do not know a Man from a Woman?</hi> reply'd the Prince peevishly. <hi>Not at all times, Sir, it seems,</hi> answer'd <hi>Villarius,</hi> almost mad, <hi>I say again,</hi> added he, <hi>That</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelia<hi>'s Wit has deceiv'd you, and that that Person that was in Bed with her, was a real Man, to her knowledg, however she has made him pass with you for a Woman. A Man with Womans Night-Cloaths on his
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:204247:51"/> Head, and a Woman bare-headed,</hi> said the Prince: here he paus'd, as if reflecting within himself. <hi>Yes, Sir,</hi> said <hi>Villarius, now you have unfolded the Riddle; under the favour of</hi> Cornelia<hi>'s Night-Cloaths you have let the Minion escape your Knowledg. How?</hi> said the Prince, looking on the Ground, as if musing still; <hi>If it was so, nothing could be more false and treacherous. There was no other way left, but under that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guise to escape you, Sir, said</hi> Villarius, <hi>and the more you will be pleas'd to reflect upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular Circumstance, the more the Cheat will appear clear to your Ʋnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. Why should she be without Night-Cloaths just at my coming, yet afterwards put them on, and never more complain of them, no in truth, scarce of her Head-ach,</hi> said the Prince. <hi>Ay, Sir, and where did she find them,</hi> said <hi>Villarius? Her Woman brought them to her,</hi> reply'd the Prince. <hi>I believe so, Sir,</hi> reply'd <hi>Villarius, when the Blade had no more use for them. She sent the Gentlewoman that was in Bed with her,</hi> said the Prince, <hi>to her Closet for some Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial. And did that Person bring it back? Villarius</hi> ask'd. <hi>No,</hi> said the Prince mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, <hi>it was that Woman that brought her Night-Cloaths. Very well, Sir, said</hi> Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, <hi>how did that modest Gentlewoman that was in Bed with</hi> Cornelia <hi>rise? before your
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:204247:52"/> face, Sir? No; odds fish,</hi> reply'd the Prince, Cornelia, <hi>I remember she bid me hold her Head while she should get out of the Bed, and though I should have had a mind to have seen her, I could not, she hugg'd me so close, notwithstanding the most violent Head-ach she had but just before complain'd of.</hi> Replied <hi>Villarius, A very convenient way to blind you, Sir, while the other esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. I begin to mistrust there was som<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Juggle in it,</hi> said the Prince, <hi>when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider well every Circumstance; in truth, sh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> did not once complain of her Head-ach all th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> night long after that, but turn'd from me an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> sigh'd often. Well, she shall never deceiv<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> me more, and if we can but get such ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opportunity, I'll warrant you I'll secur<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> her Stallion; I find I was deluded by her Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resses, her false Embraces, which she us'd n<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> longer than to serve her turn; that once done she prov'd to me, the rest of the Night, a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> cold and indifferent as if I had not been i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Bed with her. Could you blame her, Sir</hi> said <hi>Villarius, you had disappointed her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Hopes, defeated her sweet Expecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and depriv'd her of all those Joys sh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> was going to surfeit with; and would yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> after that have had her to embrace a Perso<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that had so unexpectedly disappointed her o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> all her Pleasures? Well, no more on't,</hi> sai<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Prince, <hi>I will this Afternoon dive<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:204247:52"/> this Shagrin it has brought on me, with a Glass of Wine; get half a dozen of our Friends to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether against six; send me word where you are, and I'll come to you. Villarius</hi> told the Prince he would go about it instantly, so took his leave.</p>
            <p>The Prince, at the merry meeting that Evening, was very pleasant, especially towards the latter end: at last he stole away from the Company, after he had told <hi>Villarius</hi> where he was going, and he went to visit <hi>Francelia,</hi> whom he found but just come from the Princess's Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He told her that he had been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king merry, and that he came to shew her that he was still the same towards her, that if she pleas'd to accept of a Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Heart, he had one at her Service. <hi>Had you ever more than one, Sir?</hi> answer'd <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia. No faith,</hi> replied the Prince, <hi>but that shall be yours,</hi> continued he. <hi>Then you have none to give, Sir,</hi> replied she, <hi>for that you had you gave away to the Princess in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and since that time it has been no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at your Highness's Disposal; some small sparks of it may light by accident on other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects sometimes, but the whole Flame cannot be fed, but by that Fuel which the Princess affords it. Never say that, Madam,</hi> replied the Prince; <hi>you, your Charms have made it burn far more fiercely than ever the Princess
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:204247:53"/> has done: I am very sorry, Sir,</hi> answered <hi>Francelia, that I have any thing belonging to me that serves to feed others Fires; and I would use all my Endeavours to bestow my Fuel on a Fire of my own kindling. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be so cruel as you would seem to be,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Prince, who began to be a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more frolick, and to play with his Hands. <hi>I do not think there is any Cruelty, Sir,</hi> answered she, <hi>in avoiding being cruel to my self.</hi> Saying this, she pull'd a String, after which some of her Servants enter'd the Room. The Prince presently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood the meaning of it, as though <hi>Francelia</hi> seem'd to employ one about something there; he therefore retired, telling her softly, he would not leave her so, but would declare more fully his Mind to her yet, the next time he came again to see her; with that he took his leave.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="110-162" type="pages">
            <p>
               <hi>Francelia</hi> did continually manage the Prince, as she found occasion, and as he ministred opportunity; but still she got ground of him, and finding that she had obtain'd already the greatest Ascendant over him that could be, she resolv'd on an Exploit that would shew her Master<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, and the Power of her Beauty and Wit: She found that the Prince, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the least <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a our of her, would not stick at any thing, but grant whatever
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:204247:53"/> she required, and she had all along bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Discourses that way, she thought it now high time to come to the point; wherefore, the next time that the Prince would give her an opportunity, she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to improve it, and to lay before him the Conditions on which she would yield. All this, not so much to satisfy her Conscience and pretended Vertue, as to make the Prince so surely her own, that she might command him as abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely as she pleased, in all that she should put him upon, for that Interest which had brought her over into the Isles. The Prince, on his part, resolved to yield whatever she should desire of him, to obtain his ends, did conclude within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, to subscribe to her Conditions, what ever they should be, and did with Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience wait for the next opportunity to declare fully his Mind to her, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose his weakness naked before her. Thus were our two Lovers ready to enter on a Conclusion, the next time they had the opportunity of a free Conversation.</p>
            <p>Mean time the indefatigable <hi>Villarius,</hi> who was more netl'd than ever since the last time <hi>Cornelia</hi> had outwitted him and the Prince, did make what diligence he could to learn the time of a new Assignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he was not long without being inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:204247:54"/> that by some Circumstances and Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations were made in <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s Chamber, there was some new design in hand; the Spies therefore made the best use they could of their Eyes and Ears, and at last learned for certain, that some body was to be privately admitted and entertained the following Night; they presently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>Villarius</hi> of it, and he, the Prince, and they both concerted together of the means to secure them safe, and no more to be deceived as they had been before: That which made the Prince more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest than ever, to detect <hi>Cornelia</hi> in her Inconstancy, was, that he might have more colour and just ground to break off with her, to give himself wholly up to his new Mistress, and to own her pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, which was a humour that he highly affected.</p>
            <p>The Prince having declared that he would be wholly guided by <hi>Villarius</hi> in this surprizal, at last thought fit to get three or four of his own Servants to go along with them, to place at the Doors with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, to secure whatever came out of the House, in case they should miss of the Bird in the Nest. He did not doubt but that the last danger the two Lovers had been in, would make them more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspect for the future, and that they
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:204247:54"/> knowing the Prince had a Key that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened all Doors within the House, yet he could not get into the House without the outward Gate was opened to him, and that that would be a sufficient time to give notice to the Lovers, and to let them escape. <hi>Villarius</hi> therefore had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered one of his Spies to leave a back Door upon the Latch only, that they might come in without noise.</p>
            <p>Things being thus ordered, and the hour come, the Prince and <hi>Villarius</hi> go, with the Servants, to <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; where <hi>Villarius</hi> plac'd the Men at the Fore-gate, with special order to take, dead or alive, whoever should offer to go out, and not yield to them. The Prince and he, after that, went to the back-gate, where, after the Prince was got in, <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> remain'd behind to keep Centry there, fully resolved to make sure of any Person that should sally out that way. The Prince got up Stairs, pass'd a long Gallery, and at last made a shift to lose himself in the dark, not being used to that part of the House; however, after he had blundered up and down a pretty while, he thought he heard some Voices, he hearkned, and drew nearer the place, whence he thought the Voices came, there he heard <hi>Cornelia</hi> say, <hi>I never
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:204247:55"/> spent an Evening worse in my Life than that, my Dear, though the Prince was very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, and more than ordinarily kind, because you were not there; did he but know how loathsome all his Courtship is to me, especially when you come in my Mind, he would not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me with it. I declare, that next to</hi> Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, <hi>I hate his Conversation, it is so insipid, that were it not to divert him from wholly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to that</hi> French <hi>Trollop he has lately got, (whose measures I will break or ruin all) I did not care whether I did ever see him again. It has been no little cause of wonder to me, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> replied the Blade, <hi>that you could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any Hatred against so accomplished a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, as is</hi> Villarius; <hi>a Man so powerful with the Prince, and who has serv'd you so affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately too. He has so,</hi> replied <hi>Cornelia, and that is the greatest cause of my Hatred to him, next the Love that I bear to you, which makes me despise the very Prince.</hi> Villarius <hi>fancies he merits all things from me; that no Woman in the World is able to withstand his Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and that all must truckle under that Power, which he has gained over the Prince's easy Mind; but I am resolved to so rival him in that, though I value it not in any other respect, that he shall know my Power, and his own Weakness, as well as his Masters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I despise them both, and laugh at their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses; neither could all his Courtships find
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:204247:55"/> such returns from me, as you have done, for you alone have I kept my Affection intire. And the Prince, with all his Power, is not to be compar'd with the Pleasure I now enjoy in seeing you, and being alone with you all this Night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These passionate Expressions being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with divers tender Actions, which though the Prince could not see, he could hear, did let him judg that they would be soon followed with what the Reader may imagine. This doubtless to any other Lover, would have made him violently to rush into the Chamber, with Sword in hand, and have made the Delinquent wash with his Blood, the stain laid upon his Honour; but the good natur'd Prince, far from making use of that Advantage, was a pretty while fumbling at the Door, before he could or would open it, insomuch that the Gallant had sufficient time to make his Escape out of the Chamber by the Fore-door. Yet the Prince entered the Room with his Sword drawn, and looking ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry furiously every where: <hi>Where is that Villain,</hi> said he, <hi>that dares be so bold to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear here?</hi> At these Words, and what with the Fright <hi>Cornelia</hi> had conceiv'd at the sight of a naked Sword, she fell down backwards on her Bed in a Swoon. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:204247:56"/> was any Person in the World so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man'd, as was the Prince at that Sight; he had in a moment forgot what he was come about; he thought no longer of searching after the Criminal, his Fury was blown over, and in its stead reign'd the greatest Calmness and Compassion imaginable. He let drop the Sword he had in his hand, and busied himself in recovering <hi>Cornelia</hi> from her Fit; he run to her Closet, fetch'd from thence such Cordials as he met with, he poured some into her Mouth, and at last with much to do, he brought her to Life again. He ask'd her how she did, and whether he should assist her in raising her up; she by this time having had some small time to think what she should say to the Prince, she held forth her hand, which the Prince took, and by it lifted her up; When he found that she was past danger, and that her Colour began to return, he also re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>assumed his severe Countenance, and in a grave Tone thus began to school her. <q rend="margQuotes">I must confess, Madam, that I cannot but admire at my own Goodness and Indulgence, that could afford you Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, after you had so highly abused me. You shall know, Madam, that I am not so tame as you take me to be, and that I will despise a Woman, who has so
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:204247:56"/> much forgot her self; and I will make such an Example of your Stallion, as shall deter all Persons from daring to aspire in the least, where I pretend any thing.</q> There the Prince making a pause, <hi>Cornelia</hi> had time to say, That he might be deceiv'd by outward Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and that she made no question, but that she should justify her self when she should find him divested of that Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Fury, which from his Brow did threaten her too severely. <q rend="margQuotes">That will not do with me now, Madam, replied the Prince, I have heard too much how unworthily you reviled me to your Minion, to admit of any excuse, from a Person so unworthy my Favours. Yes, Sir, said <hi>Cornelia,</hi> I did speak all that in my Anger, and just Resentments could suggest to me, so soon as I heard some bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at my Chamber-door, imagining that none could have the Confidence to come and disturb my rest, at such an Hour, when I was retired, but a Person trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with Chymerial Jealousie, as you shew your self to be. In revenge I did speak things loud enough, that they might be heard by you, that I might give you some Disturbance, for your unkind censuring of my Actions, and the ill opinion you harbour of me; but
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:204247:57"/> to whom did I speak those things, Sir? That you know, Madam, and you may save me the Trouble to tell it you. Where have you hid that Wretch? Sir, you have free Liberty to search all Corners in this House, and to take your just Revenge on any Delinquents you shall find here, but till then, I wish I might see your Highness take a more serene Air. I spoke those Words to none but my self, Sir, and it was my Passion that forc'd them from my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censed Mind, as a Punishment for your distrustful humour. I am not to be any longer impos'd upon now, Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Prince, and it was enough for you to deceive me once, with the shift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your Night-dresses on your Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and not to go about to abuse m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> once again to my Face: But I trifle here, I see, and I will find him out here or secure him hereafter, that he shall never more dare to lift up his Eyes, where I have any thoughts.</q>
               <hi>Cornelia</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered not a word, but seemed not to be well; and the Prince fearing that she was going once again to work on his too easy temper, went out of the Chamber<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> he met upon the Stairs <hi>Villarius,</hi> who wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> going to see what was become of him. The Prince told him, that thoug<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:204247:57"/> the Gallant had escap'd him, he had heard enough to convince him of the baseness of the Woman. <hi>Villarius</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, that he had secured the Man, and sent him where he should be kept safe, till your Highness shall examine him. After that they retired, the Prince giving him a full account of his Proceeding with <hi>Cornelia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time the <hi>French</hi> Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour in the Isles, who had been instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in the breaking of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned League, did give frequent Visits to <hi>Francelia,</hi> and so did his Wife, which Visits <hi>Francelia</hi> return'd again. <hi>Artabaces,</hi> who was privy to the <hi>French</hi> Cabal, and who all along kept up that, and <hi>France<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>'s Interest together, in whose House the Prince had had divers private Meetings with <hi>Francelia,</hi> having been informed all along of her Progress on the Prince's Mind, and she having told him that all things were now ripe, and that she was going to put the last hand to the work. He made a very magnificent Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at a new-built House of his, where were invited the Prince, <hi>Francelia,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Embassadour and his Lady, with divers other Persons of Quality of the <hi>French</hi> Party. The Prince, whom <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> had the next Morning brought to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:204247:58"/> see the Delinquent Lover, had the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to hear him own his Crime; which ingenious Confession oblig'd the Prince to inflict no other Punishment upon him, but a Banishment, with Threatning<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that if ever he attempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of that nature again, he should find a more rigorous usage. After that the Prince prepar'd to go to the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, with a Resolution fully to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>close his Mind to <hi>Francelia,</hi> and to bring things to a Conclusion.</p>
            <p>Things being so far brought to maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty betwixt the two Lovers, though not with the knowledg of one anothers In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, a true understanding, and a good success, cou'd not chuse but follow; wherefore the Prince applying himself closely, after Dinner, to the Courtship of his Mistress, and willing to clear that point on which she had so long insisted, he fell upon that Theme himself, and told her, That he was resolved to do any thing that she should require of him, provided that she would after all be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to him. She made answer, that she had long since declar'd to him, that she wanted not Respect and over Love, to gratify him in any thing that he could require of her; but that she could not bring her self to submit to that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:204247:58"/> which a closer Conjunction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, would bring upon her, so long as there was no Marriage in the case. <q rend="margQuotes">Nay, if that be all, Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Prince, I'll marry you over and over, after what form and manner you shall like best: Come, come, we'll go about it immediately; no better time than now, we shall have so many Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses: Come, who will lend us a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulary, and who shall be the Priest? Here's a Match made, my Lord, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he, and a Wedding at hand; who shall we have for Bride-men and Bride-maids? Not so fast, Sir, reply'd <hi>Francelia,</hi> you are making a Jest of what I am very serious in: Who I? reply'd the Prince, not in the least, I assure you: I'll go about it presently, and give more private orders for getting all things in a readiness for your Satisfaction.</q> With that, the Prince over-joy'd that he and his Mistress were come to an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though with different Intentions, the one endeavouring all things to be done with a great deal of Solemnity and Circumspection, while the other had no further thoughts in it, but to let her have her humour, in a frollick, so long as it work'd his ends with her. There was four or five persons pitch'd upon to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:204247:59"/> be present at the Agreement of the two Lovers, who retired in a private Room, where one in the habit of a Priest mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled over the Matrimony, and so both Parties were agreed. The Prince expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a World of Impatience to come to an Enjoyment after all this Condescenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: those that were privy to the business, caus'd a Bridal Bed to be fitted, where in the presence of two Persons the Prince Bedded and enjoy'd his <hi>French</hi> Mistress; and he being of a humour, as not to care much to toil or take pains to obtain his Pleasures, as he had frequently declar'd, and that he lov'd to find some work rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy done to his hands, and moreover ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been that day very well plyed with Healths, to make him the less capable of discernment, he never troubled himself, nor found fault afterwards, for not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things the first Night he enjoy'd his Mistress, according to that height o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Vertue and Innocence that she always had professed.</p>
            <p>Thus had <hi>Francelia</hi> the Satisfaction to be assur'd, that after such a Tryal she had put the Prince upon, he could not refuse her any thing that she should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of him; all her Policy therefor<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which she us'd afterwards, was to kee<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Prince from falling into Relapse<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:204247:59"/> with <hi>Cornelia,</hi> and to entertain and keep up his Affections towards her self, at the same pitch to which she had brought him, in which she made use of all her subtile Policy and Wit, with the super-addition of her other Charms, by which she easily obtain'd all that she would from him, to the advantage of the <hi>French,</hi> beyond all that the <hi>French</hi> Ambassadours, and the <hi>French</hi> Court-Pensioners could do; inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that when at sometimes the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of other Princes, did represent with so much reason, and on such sure grounds, that it was against the Prince's and the Nation's Interest, to yield such and such things to the <hi>French,</hi> which would so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the Prince, that he was ready to recal his Word from the <hi>French</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, which he had assur'd those other State-Ministers that he would do; <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia</hi> would work more with him in one Night, than they could do with all their Just Reasonings; and would so turn the Scales again before Morning, that those Ministers well saw they should never be able to bring the Prince to any reasonable Terms, so long as he lay in the Arms of that <hi>French Dalila.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francelia</hi> having thus brought her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs to pass, as to the firm Establishing of her Interest in the Prince's Bosom, she
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:204247:60"/> had no more to do but destroy <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s, that she might rise on her debasement; but because those Titles and Honours which had been conferr'd on <hi>Cornelia,</hi> were not to be taken off, she soon did work with the Prince to make her as Great in all respects; she was not long without great Titles, and without some other Testimonies of the Prince's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. The Prince did not only fill her Coffers, but her Belly also, so that at last the Princess taking notice of it, she plainly told <hi>Francelia</hi> what her thoughts were of her. <hi>Francelia</hi> being conscious of her guilt, and that to go about to deny a thing which she would have to come to light, would but aggravate things with the Princess, and make them appear the worse; in time she little by little drew her self from her presence, and acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Prince with what the Princess had laid to her Charge. There present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followed Consultations betwixt the Prince, his Mistress, and all the <hi>French</hi> Ministers and Partisans, how the thing should be carried; the Prince was for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy, and <hi>Francelia</hi> forbidding open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to all; but the Prince upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture advice, carried it his way, and she was at last deliver'd of a Son in <hi>Artabasus</hi>'s Lodgings, the whole business being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:204247:60"/> with all the privacy imaginable, there being a Man-Midwife in readiness to that purpose, who took care ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Instructions he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, to convey the Child away, who was for some considerable time kept in the Country, at a Farmers House, where it was Baptiz'd by an appointed Chaplain, and had for Godfathers and Godmothers such as the Country would afford. But <hi>Francelia</hi> being wearied at last in remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obscure, did so work with the Prince, that notwithstanding <hi>Cornelia</hi>'s last Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords towards the Princess, to endeavour the suppressing of the growing Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure of <hi>Francelia;</hi> she was not long after Intituled to great Dignities, and her Son also some time after.</p>
            <p>Now did <hi>Francelia</hi> look upon her self as come to the height she had all-along aim'd at, and she did not a little glory also, though in private, and amongst those that were of the Cabal, of her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Prince's Wife; and when it ever reach'd the Prince's Ears, though he would sometimes be a little displeas'd at it, yet when he considered that all that Pageantry was perform'd, but to obtain his Ends of his Mistress with the more ease and quicker dispatch, would laugh at it, and say, <hi>'Twas fitting she should have
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:204247:61"/> her Humour a little, as well as he had his.</hi> He caus'd a Magnificent Appartment to be made ready, and very richly furnish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for her at Court; he own'd her pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly for his Mistress, and the young Child for his Son: And by the Assidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Visits, and the whole days and nights he spent with her, he gave all the World sufficiently to understand that she had made her self Mistress of his Mind; and that she had got such an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendant over him, that all the Policy in the World was never able to remove. Now she had so well perform'd the first part of her Commission, that there was no fear left in the <hi>French</hi> Ministers, but that she would succeed in the rest, to the height of their Expectations. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now things were put forwards in <hi>France,</hi> for her to bring to perfection here. The Great Senate was grown too troublesome, and was too prying into the French Affairs; they amongst the rest, would have the Prince to recal all his Subjects out of the French Service, both by Sea and Land; and while they were busy about such necessary things, for the good of the Nation, there came a very great Embassy from <hi>Tyrannides,</hi> and in order that they should be receiv'd accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Merits, and the Grandure of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:204247:61"/> the King they came from. <hi>Francelia</hi> perswaded the Prince to Adjourn the Great Senate for their better Reception. This Embassy consisted of divers Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; the chiefest of which were a Duke, an Arch-Bishop, and <hi>Brillano;</hi> and these were follow'd with about 400 Persons of all sorts and degrees. But the Grand Senat being grown so obstinate, as to oppose all the particulars about which they were come; <hi>Francelia</hi> was set to work, and perform'd her business so ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, that <hi>Tyrannides</hi> had full Leisure and Liberty to compleat his Conquests against his Enemies: She obtain'd that the Prince's Subjects should not be recall'd from the French Service; she dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded the Prince from concluding a League Offensive and Defensive with <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavia.</hi> And to these purposes, because the Grand Senate had declar'd they would proceed on no Business whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, till those, and other things of that nature were first done, she got the Prince to Adjourn them from time to time: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst which Adjournments and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogations, there was one, when the greatest urgency of Affairs, and the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which highly threatned that Nation, requir'd most their Assembling, in order to bring to condign Punishment, all
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:204247:62"/> such as had been Instrumental in carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a dangerous Plot against these Isles. Then was it that <hi>Francelia</hi> employ'd all her Policy, Charms and Wit, to bring the Prince to so extraordinary an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the great prejudice of the Isles, and which it was impossible he should ever have been brought to, while he was himself: Wherefore means were found out, so much to alienate his Mind from his own Interest, that he should be brought to act absolutely contrary to his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign. Amongst divers was propos'd, but few thought proper, <hi>Francelia</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive none but she her self had design'd; she only wanted two more of her Sex to assist her in it, which having got, and full Instructions how to manage the Prince to the advantage of the Plot, she fell to work. The Prince had divers times mention'd, that he had a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to be throughly merry with her, to dissipate some Shagrins which the late disturbances had rais'd in his Mind. <q rend="margQuotes">You shall not want that any longer, Sir, <hi>Francelia</hi> told him, and if you please but to name the day, I'll undertake for the rest, and shall endeavour all I can possible to give you some agreeable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version.</q> The Prince, who did not care how soon he were freed from some time
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:204247:62"/> of those Agitations which the searching too deep into the Plot wrought in his Mind, told her, <q rend="margQuotes">The sooner the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that he did not care if it was that very Evening; nay, I design to make a Night on't, <hi>continued he,</hi> and to cast off all Cares, Trouble and Thoughts, except of Mirth, during that time.</q>
               <hi>Francelia</hi> presently agreed to it, and prepar'd a magnificent Banquet, with divers sorts of Musick, and variety of pleasant Liquors. Those Persons also which compos'd the Company, had screw'd their Mirth and Wits to the highest pitch, that nothing should be wanting that could produce Delights, and banish thence all Cares and Thoughts; in a word, that Night was to be wholly dedicated to <hi>Baccus</hi> and to <hi>Venus:</hi> And in effect, it prov'd a Debauch of the highest nature, the whole night being spent with Drinking and Toying; so that the Prince was never more enrowl'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Bacchus</hi>'s Banner than he was that night; and in the morning, when the Company began to be so tir'd as to part, <hi>Francelia</hi> to fill up the measure, and come to the Point and Conclusion, towards which, all the Extravagancies which were committed that night were so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny steps, she with the two other great
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:204247:63"/> Ladies and the Prince retir'd into another more private Place, where to make a full Conquest of him, before he should cool so much as to admit of any second Thought or Reflections, <hi>Francelia</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the two other Ladies who were complaining of Heat, to strip; and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to it, she began her self to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen her Bosom, to take in a little Air. That Allurement made the Prince to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire a further view of those Charms which rais'd his Desires, and because that <hi>Francelia</hi> insisted upon having the two other Ladies do the same; the Prince not only us'd many Intreaties to obtain that Favour from them, but assisted them also to undress; so that at last, following <hi>Francelia</hi>'s Example, they pull'd off so long that they left nothing on, to cover them, but what Nature had furnish'd them withal. Thus did those three naked Ladies stand before the Prince, not unlike the three Goddesses, <hi>Juno, Pallas</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> before <hi>Paris.</hi> The Prince ravish'd with such a Spectacle, did examine every part with his Eyes, with all the Curiosity imaginable; and because the Ladies would dress again, he bethought himself of proposing some Diversion in their undress; amongst di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that were mention'd, the sport of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:204247:63"/> Questions and Commands was pitch'd upon. They employ'd some time at it, and frequently when it came to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies turns to Command, they would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose upon the Prince, the drinking a Glass of Wine to each of their Healths, to bear up his Spirits: And the good Prince thought he could do no less, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital of those Favours he obtain'd from them, and to keep up the Frolick also, on his side. At last <hi>Francelia</hi> finding that all things were as she would have them, to give the word that should cause a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Amazement through the whole Nation, it being her turn to Rule; She ask'd the Prince whether he would have two Commands and one Question, or two Questions and one Command? the Prince desired one Command and two Questions. She ask'd him first, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would not be glad to be so Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, as hence-forth to Govern without the Grand Senate, and have no further occasion for them? Next she ask'd, Who he thought the happiest Monarch in the World? The Prince having answer'd to those two Questions as he thought fit, she Commanded him to Dissolve the Grand Senat. Her Command was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily obey'd, and the very next Morning put in Execution; in part by a Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:204247:64"/> which was the first step to its Dissolution, notwithstanding all that the sober Party could alledge to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and to the wonder of all the World.</p>
            <p>Thus what all the Arts of the most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd Politicks and Rhetorick could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have been able to bring about in a long Succession of Time, was done with ease and Diligence by a Woman's Tongue and Tail; for which she had the Applause of all that Party, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, of her Lord and Soveraign <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannides.</hi> This Master-piece made her fit, in the Opinion of all the Caballists, to be, not only admitted into the most secret Consultations after that, but also to have her Voice in all the Affairs that were negotiated at home and abroad. That was the reason, that after the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmundus,</hi> to which she was made privy, as to all other Designs; she had the Curiosity, with another La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of great Quality, to go to see his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as it lay in a Palace, on which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving smil'd, she said, That many should follow him, rather than that Work so well begun for the good of the French, shou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d fall short of their Hopes and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations. Yet, how great soever her Expectations were that way, they were
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:204247:64"/> not without some mixture of Fears and Apprehensions; she was frequently heard to say, <hi>That it was good to make Hay while the Sun shin'd, and to provide a Cloak against a Storm.</hi> She, like an expert Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician, would provide against an adverse Fortune in the highest of Prosperity, as being indeed the most fit and proper time so to do; that made her to drain the Prince's Purse, as well as his Body, getting from him, when any Money was stirring, vast Sums to lay up as well as to defray her exhorbitant Expences at Gaming. That made <hi>Helliana</hi> one day to say, pleasantly to the Prince, who seem'd unwilling to bestow 20 pieces of Gold for a <hi>Pollony</hi> Dog which she fancy'd much, That the Prince had given more thousands of pounds for a French Bitch than he would give of pieces of Gold for a much prettier Creature. <hi>Francelia</hi> was a very great lover of Cards, would play suitable to her Quality, and sit up whole nights at it, insomuch, that what with fretting at the loss of a very considerable Sum, and with sitting up for several nights, in hopes to regain some back, (but her Countrey-Men being too cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for her that way, made her lose more and more) she so heated her Body, that she had upon it a dangerous fit of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:204247:65"/> Sickness, which gave the good Prince a great deal of trouble, and cost him ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Tears and Gold to repair her loss.</p>
            <p>It was well known, how frequently she had private Conferences with <hi>Brilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> and a Secretary of State, concerning that scurvy Discovery of the Plot, and how she influenc'd the Prince to slight all the Evidences that appear'd to prove the same; and now it was thought fit to proffer to her Service an <hi>Hibernian</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who had been formerly employ'd about the meanest Offices at Court, and by her bold Confidence had rais'd her self to some higher Employ. She had been Examin'd and Try'd, and had been found a fit Instrument for <hi>Francelia</hi>'s purposes, so she became from a Vile In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable Wretch a very great States-woman, and a great part of the Secrets were imparted to her, and she so well acted her part, that <hi>Francelia</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended her to the Prince's Favour. It was by her means afterwards that all sorts of Pamphlets and Verses were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd to <hi>Francelia,</hi> who would shew them unto the Prince, who employ'd Persons after that to find out the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of them.</p>
            <p>Of several Amorous Intrigues which <hi>Francelia</hi> had at divers times, the Prince
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:204247:65"/> did never suspect her but twice, and the first time too was but for a very small time, and very superficially. One <hi>Ʋrbiru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> for Diversion, did cast his Eyes on <hi>Francelia,</hi> and his Amorous Looks were repay'd with such Glances from her, as made him see, that his Person would be as acceptable, as had always been his Wit and Conversation; his own Inclinations spurr'd him on, and he found he had not many steps to make that way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of her Advances towards him; they presently understood one another, and it was not long e're he receiv'd from her such Assurances of her Good-will, that he waited but for time and opportunity to improve his Fortune. Neither was she on her part backward in the least, to let him know how much she coveted some greater Indearment with him; and she so prest him, that knowing himself to be in no condition to give her all the satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that she required, without doing her some prejudice, he still went back, as she prest forward, which made her but the more eagerly to pursue the Game, in the Opinion that my Lord <hi>Ʋrbirupa</hi> had some new Amour in hand, into which, according as she might be inclin'd, he would discover his Intrigues with her. One day that <hi>Ʋrbirupa</hi> was come to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:204247:66"/> pay those Respects to her, which of late he had frequently done; she told him, that of all things in the World she won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd most, that Men should make it their business to insinuate into Womens Affections, on the bare account of so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and without drawing any further advantage, than to boast of it after. He being surpriz'd at this free Declaration, could no longer forbear, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the condition he was in, which had made him to defer from time to time, giving her that Satisfaction which she ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and that he was as eager to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow upon her, but for the above-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Circumstance he found himself in; that setting aside all those Considerations, which had detain'd him so long from the Enjoyment of that which he so earnestly desired, and of the prejudice that the Prince might receive from it at the third hand; he only told her, that she might be mistaken in him, and that what she took for meer Gallantry and Custom, was an effect of her singular Perfections, and of his Sense and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, only mixt perhaps with too much of profound Respect for the Mistress of his Prince; but that now he had laid aside all other considerations, to give himself wholly up to Love, and to her
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:204247:66"/> Service; in short they made use of the present opportunity, being alone, and without likelihood of being disturb'd, and for the present they both were very well satisfied with one another, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in a secret Correspondency du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring some time.</p>
            <p>At length <hi>Francelia</hi> found her self Ill, and perceiving that she was worse and worse, and that <hi>Ʋrbirupa</hi> grew remiss in his Visits to her, she sent to him to desire him to see her: He mistrusting what it was about, deferred answering her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, still putting off his appearing with some pretence or other, till at last they having press'd him beyond excuse, he could no longer put off waiting on her, he went immediately to <hi>Francelia</hi>'s A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, and found her all in Tears, who being left alone with him, told him, That he was certainly the most perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man alive, and that he had intirely ruin'd her; with that she declar'd in what a Condition she was, that she was the most miserable Wretch in the whole World, and that she did not know how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have her self to the Prince. <hi>Ʋrbirupa</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her in such a Passion, after a little pause, told her, That he was sorry any such thing had happen'd, that it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to him, he was himself in such a
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:204247:67"/> Condition; and upon redoubling of her Lamentations, he bid her to be of good Comfort, and not afflict her self so much, assuring that he would take care all things should be well, and the Prince have not so much as the least suspicion of it, only he bid her to stave off the Prince but two or three days longer from her Embraces, and by that time all things should be so ordered, that no prejudice should possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly come to her. In fine, <hi>Ʋrbirupa,</hi> who abounded in Wit and good Language, did so well make use of them both to <hi>Francelia,</hi> that in short, she wholly relied on his address and good management, and so let him go about that work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋrbirupa</hi> being then highly in favour with the Prince, and one of those with whom he did use to divert himself pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately; he went immediately and found out the Prince, and presently put him on a Discourse of Women. <hi>They are, Sir,</hi> said he, <hi>but as we make them, and we have the happiness not to ingage with any but such, whose Modesty, strait-lac'd Virtue, or Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, are no Impediments to our Pleasures: we are for Freedom, for all sorts of Liberties, in which we feast all our Senses at once. That, I must confess, is very agreeable,</hi> repli'd the Prince, <hi>and I am much of your mind, that Greatness does but obstruct our Pleasures. Ah!
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:204247:67"/> Sir,</hi> said <hi>Ʋrbirupa, did you but know, did you but see our ways, you would certainly be very well pleas'd with them, and you would not be long without making some Tryal that way. I have a mind to have a frolick that way, to see the humour of it,</hi> reply'd the Prince; <hi>when do you think we might do any thing of that Nature? When you please, Sir,</hi> reply'd the other, <hi>I know a place where there are three or four of the Prettiest, Witti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, Ingenious, merry Creatures in the World; they are incomparable Company, Sir,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued he, <hi>and such as would infinitely please your Humour. Name but your time, Sir,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he, <hi>and I shall give order that the Coast may be clear for your admittance, and those only you shall appoint to wait on you there. Faith,</hi> reply'd the Prince, <hi>I care not and if it be this Night, get you two or three more of our Company to meet there, and I'll be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to go along with you. Ʋrbirupa</hi> having assur'd him he would not fail to do all things according to his desire; he went his ways to give the necessary Orders, and return'd again to the Prince, to let him know all things were in a readiness to entertain him, and that the rest of the Company was there already, though none of them knew the Prince should be there.</p>
            <p>The Prince having disguis'd himself a
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:204247:68"/> little, went with <hi>Ʋrbirupa</hi> to the Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, not a little tickl'd in his Fancy, with the surprizal the Company would be in at his coming, as also at the singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar pastime that he expected to find there. It is certain that the whole Company did all they could to divert the Prince, but above all <hi>Ʋrbirupa</hi> with his gay Humour and Ingenious Wit, insomuch that the Prince heartily thank'd him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested he never was so merry in his life, and he did taste of all the Variety that was offer'd, with a great deal of Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and without the least Scruple. At last the Company broke up, because the Prince grew Sleepy, and the Prince went home well satisfied with that night's Adventure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋrbirupa</hi> having thus far play'd his part, with all the Success he could wish, and without the least distrust to the Prince, the next day he went to acquaint <hi>Francelia</hi> with it, and gave her some di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to govern her self towards the Prince the next time he should come near her; and that in case he should not come of himself the next day, she should not fail, to invite him the day after to some Entertainment, that his too long absence might not break their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures. <hi>Francelia</hi> had no need to use any
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:204247:68"/> Invitation, for the Prince came to her the next day in the Evening, with whom he stay'd the best part of the night, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somuch that now they had a very easy Game to play of it. Some five or six days after <hi>Francelia,</hi> according to her Kew, so soon as she saw the Prince, did make a sad and lamentable Complaint to him of the Condition she was in, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doling her misfortune, and the misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness of her Condition. The Prince who expected not such a Reception, and that was wholly ignorant of the business, was not a little startled at it. He ask'd her what was the matter with her? <hi>What mean you, Madam,</hi> continued he, <hi>and who do you take me for? I mean, Sir,</hi> said she in a great Passion, <hi>that you have ruin'd me, you have undone me, I am lost, I am undone for ever.</hi> The Prince more and more amaz'd at her Transports, looking on her with some concern: <hi>Explain your self, Madam,</hi> continu'd he, <hi>and put me out of suspence. What need I tell you, Sir, that which you know so well, and feel already. Still a Riddle to me, and I shall continue in a Cloud, except you will express your self so as that I may understand you.</hi> At last with much to do, and not without violent Reproaches, she let the Prince understand that he had made her very ill: The Prince startled
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:204247:69"/> at the first news of it, went about to excuse himself, and to plead his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, but that serv'd but to exasperate her the more, insomuch that she fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to such Passions, or at least did so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently well counterfeit them, that it put the good Prince on serious Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He began to think of his last frol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licking night, and of what he had then done, and concluded in himself, against himself, taking all the blame to himself, and freely confessing his Guilt to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged Mistress, most humbly and hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begging her Pardon, with a thousand Protestations that he knew nothing of it, or he had not been so base as to have come near her, and that at that very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant he was as free from any such di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemper, as ever he was in all his Life. He further assur'd her, that he had no ill Opinion of her in the least; that he took all upon himself, and that he would highly make her amends for the wrong he had done her: With that he set him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to caress her, which brought her a little out of her dumps; and some few days after, the Prince finding himself ill, he went again to her, to confess and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg his Fault, and to perfect the Reconciliation; assigning her, besides a very considerable Sum of Mony with
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:204247:69"/> which he bought his Peace, which serv'd to go to the <hi>Bath</hi> suitable to her Rank and Grandure, where she resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v'd to stay, and did stay till the Prince begg'd of her to return to him, which she did at her leisure, and when she thought fit. She remain'd for some time after her return under the Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians Hands; and though the Prince was perfectly then recover'd of his Illness, she would not let him Embrace her of a long time after, but still persisted in the Opinion, at least seemingly, that the Prince could not be well so long as she remain'd Ill, seeing that he had been the first attack'd by that Distemper under which she still lay languishing. This oblig'd the Prince to inquire a little more narrowly into the matter, and at last he was inform'd by one of his own Physicians, who he had sent to take care of her in Conjunction with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that her Distemper proceeded from another Cause, than he imagin'd, and that it render'd her incapable of Caressing him as she us'd to do, but that in a short time she would recover, though peradventure with a disability o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bearing any more Children. The Prince desir d the Doctor to continue his Cares towards her; and so was forc'd to rest
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:204247:70"/> satisfy'd for sometime longer: In short, the Prince was never at ease till she was recover'd; nor then neither, to speak the truth; for never was there any Money stirring, either in the Privy-Purse, in the Exchequer, or from beyond-Seas, but she would have her share of it, no matter how the Prince resented it, or how he was censur'd by the Nation: It was to advance the French Interest that she had acted all along; and why should she not share in the Gold that came from thence as well as such which she knew very well had not perform'd so much, nor merited more than she had done; and to make all things sure, no sooner had she got a considerable Sum together, but it was sent into <hi>France</hi> in good Gold, till it was pretty well drain'd; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in Silver, under pretence of Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and other things made up in Casks: It was with those immense Sums that she has built a most Magnificent Palace, and that she at present keeps as great a Rank at the French Court, as any one that is of the Blood-Royal, though she has lost prodigiously at play since her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus was the good Prince play'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by his ungrateful French Mistress, who not contented to play false with him,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:204247:70"/> had the Impudence afterwards to task him with Crimes, that she her self was guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of; making him pay for her Lascivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, and make an Atonement for her Faults.</p>
            <p>The other time that the Prince accus'd <hi>Francelia</hi> of Falshood, he had better success than in this former Intrigue, through the Assistance of one of her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who was not at first come into the Prince's Interests, as she did afterwards upon some distaste, which is not worth the mentioning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tyrannides</hi> had sent to the Court of the Isles, a certain Clergy-man, with the Character of Publick Minister, to negotiate something of great moment there with <hi>Francelia,</hi> and the French Pensioners at Court; and being a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of a Noble Family, of an high Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, rarely Educated, of a very fine Presence, and a very good Meen, and a great stock of Wit and Complaisance, with a full Purse; all these excellent Qualifications did render him acceptable in all ingenious Companies, and most highly coveted by the softer Sex, to which he was naturally very much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd, and very well endow'd in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects to do them Service: But above all, under pretence of private Conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:204247:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:204247:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:204247:72"/> he had access almost at all times at <hi>Francelia</hi>'s Lodgings, where he would sometimes pass whole Nights at play, and though he would lose sometimes very consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably, yet he would never be wanting to gratify the Servants, which acquired him a more free Access in most places where he resorted: After some time, when that he had dispatch'd the best part of the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness he came for, he did not for that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease the number of his Visits, but only altered the Property of them, both as to Privacy and Business, which made him also to alter his Discourses; for whereas formerly they were of Affairs and politick Designs, which he would conclude with some slight amorous Complement; now his whole Theme was Love, and only some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to blind those that would intrude, he would superficially touch on some State Affair. His Person was not to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked, as I have said already, and with that he was very agreeable Company; besides, the Prince began to grow ancient, and not so full of Courtship consequently, as formerly: All these things together, made <hi>Francelia</hi> to open her Eyes, her Ears, and at last, her very Heart to this <hi>Sancti Pater</hi>'s Charms, while he was admiring and praising hers, so that there was Charms for Charms, and both parties were
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:204247:72"/> very well satisfied in Conversation one with another. This Trade continued a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty while before notice was taken, and all that could be made of it, when look'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a little more narrowly, was, that they diverted themselves at Cards, and in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursing of Passages at the French Court. Mean time, Love, who never is at a stay, increasing in these two Lovers Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soms, they began to find that their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance was more troublesome to them than it used to be; and that they might very well dispence with them, and not be the least incommoded. What the <hi>Sancti Pater</hi> said, was seconded by <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia,</hi> who from thence took new Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures; and whereas formerly the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence-Chamber was rarely without some Servants in it, and the Anti-Chamber con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually full of Waiters, very frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly she would send forth those that wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in her Chamber, on trifling Busines<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, that she might have the greater Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for Action. Amongst those that were so served was one of her Women, who took it so at Heart, that she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved within her self to play them a Trick for it so soon as she had an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, however she gave no Signs in the least of Discontent; on the contrary seem'd as well pleas'd as ever, having
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:204247:73"/> found means privately so to post her self, as to see and hear all that past betwixt the two passionate Lovers.</p>
            <p>Our two Politicians, as well in Love, as in State-Affairs, did gradually ascend to the highest step of their Imaginary Felicity, that they might daily relish new Joys, and taste fresh Pleasures; and though at first they run, not headlong, to a full fruition, they toy'd sufficiently, and spoke a Thousand passionate things; if one call'd the other his Joy, he was call'd again, her Life: Thus all the most endearing Expressions that Love could inspire them with, were utter'd round; and with ten thousand Daliances repeated. All these things did the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Spie behold, but not as sufficient yet to give her that full satisfaction of that sweet Revenge which she long'd for; wherefore, with a World of impatience she waited for that she expected would follow of course.</p>
            <p>The Prince, of late, had divers times, when he came to visit his unconstant Mistress, found the Door shut, and she either retir'd into her Closet, or lay'd down to rest, as not being well. These Excuses and Pretences had at first pass'd current with him, but at last, he began to grow weary of them, and it rais'd
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:204247:73"/> some Suspicions in him. These distrusts were sometimes after blown up into a flame of Jealousie by an unexpected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident. The Prince having one day gone to <hi>Francelia</hi>'s Lodgings, as he us'd to do, was told, That she had had an ill night, that she was newly laid down to endeavour to Sleep a little, and had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven order, That no body should disturb her: The Prince willing she should be obey'd, pass'd from her Chamber Door into that Room where the Spie was on the Watch, more by meer chance, than with any design; and perceiving her sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting very attentive, he came up to her, in order to further inform himself concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Mistresses Health; but first ask'd, What she did there so pensive alone? The cunning Gipsie, glad of the opportunity that presented it self, to begin the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Mystery of Iniquity; answer'd, That that place answering to <hi>Francelia</hi>'s Beads-head, she was hearkening there, to know when she might go in to her, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving her the trouble to ring the Bell, which might cause her some di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbance: but she deliver'd this with such a Stile, and with such an Accent, as would sufficiently give to understand to any mean Capacity, that she spoke Iro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically. That gave the Prince the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osity
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:204247:74"/> of leaning his Head against the Wainscote to hearken; and he had his Desire; he did hear, not only one Voice, not only <hi>Francelia</hi>'s, but another in Consort with hers; but though he could make a shift to distinguish two dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Voices, yet they whispered so low, that it was impossible for him to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand what they said. This, however, did highly disturb him, insomuch that he could not forbear, as in a Surprise, to ask, what was the meaning of this? and prest the Woman very earnestly to unriddle the Business to him. But he was answered, That she used to follow her Ladies Orders implicitly, and never presumed to dive further into her Secrets than she her self was pleased to lay open. This Answer did but disquiet the Prince the more, and he earnestly press'd her to inform him in this Mystery. She did excuse her self, and pleaded Ignorance, but in such a manner as but confirmed the Prince the more in his Distrust. Our subtile Spie having at last screw'd up the Prince's Jealousie to that hight she desired, she began to relent, and to seem to be desirous to comply with his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, and in Conclusion, upon Promises that the Prince would stand her Friend, and would amply gratify her, she told
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:204247:74"/> him, that of truth <hi>Francelia</hi> had but feign'd an Indisposition, to have the greater liberty to entertain a Friend of hers in private, without disturbancc. This did but increase the Prince's Desires of knowing more, which made him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat his Assurances of Kindnesses and Reward to her. At last, she told him, That there was no such great Mystery in the Business; neither, that it was but what he had allow'd of before; and that the same person was with her now, whom he had formerly found in private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with <hi>Francelia</hi> more than once, when he had retir'd, and left them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>I understand you now,</hi> said the Prince, <hi>it is her Countryman</hi> Sancti Pater; <hi>but now the case is alter'd,</hi> continu'd he; <hi>it is true, that I did allow of private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences between them, so long as he had Business of State to negotiate with her, but those things have been made an end of long since; and I know not what now he can have to communicate so privately to her, that I must not have admittance. Though I have sign'd all the Acts of their former Conferences, I shall not give my Consent to this Privy-one. Does he frequently do this? Yes, Sir,</hi> reply'd the Woman, <hi>but I humbly beg your Pardon for having not inform'd you sooner of it, not knowing, but that it was
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:204247:75"/> as formerly by your Consent. My consent,</hi> reply'd the Prince, <hi>it's so from it, that I will break their Measures, and spoyl their Intrigue; but I will first be sure, before I make any noise about it; in which, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire your Assistance.</hi> The Woman return'd him an Assurance, that she would for his Service, do all that lay in her power. <hi>Can you not so contrive,</hi> said the Prince, <hi>as that I may come upon them unawares, and surprise them when they are retir'd together? I shall do my endeavour, Sir,</hi> answer'd she, <hi>to give you that satisfaction, and I shall not fail, in order to it, to give you timely notice, the next time they are together, then your Highness may proceed in the Business as you shall think fit.</hi> The Prince intreated her to do so, and to take no further notice of it for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, no more than he would, that he might the more surely surprise them; which she having promis'd to do, the Prince went his way, with more distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances in his Head, than he had brought along with him, though he had had some Jealousies before.</p>
            <p>The Woman mean time continued her diligent Watch, as well as the two Lovers did their secret Conversations, that she might find out an opportunity of gratifying the Prince according to his
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:204247:75"/> desires. She had no occasion to wait long for it, the very next day offer'd her what she desired. <hi>Francelia</hi> having feigned to be indispos'd, <hi>Sancti Pater</hi> came to give her some Consolation, as he us'd to do; so soon as he was come, <hi>Francelia</hi> gave more express Orders than ever, that no Body should disturb her not till Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, because that she had some extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary business that required great haste to be dispatch'd by Morning; this she told to that very Woman that spy'd her Actions, having call'd for her into her Chamber, where, for a shew of business, divers Papers were laid open on the Table, and a Pen and Ink got ready: but on the contrary, all that did but confirm the Woman, that there was something to be done that Night, on the Interest of Love more than on that of State; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore presently after she went her self to give the Prince notice, that the Party was come, and that he was to lose no time. This was about Nine at Night, the Prince came with all the Privacy he could, and had the Curiosity to go to the place to listen, whether he could o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-hear any of their Discourse. All this while the Woman had conceal'd from his knowledge the Peep-hole she had, whereby she could see what was done in
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:204247:76"/> the best part of the Chamber, but now she brought the Prince to it, and there he saw Wonders, and heard the <hi>Sancti Pater</hi> say: <hi>Now is the happy moment, in which I shall drink with long draughts, of those Sweets that flows from those delicious Streams, of which I have hitherto had but tempting sip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, which have but the more increast my unquenched Spirit. You see what I have done for you,</hi> reply'd <hi>Francelia; you have all sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crific'd now to your Love, and the Prince him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self lies neglected, to bestow on you, my Dear, with a more profuse hand, all that I am able to give you. I dare not think too much upon it, Madam,</hi> replied he, <hi>lest I should die for Joy before my time; that is, before I am wrapt in Extasie in your Charming Embraces. Why lose we time, Madam,</hi> added he, <hi>a time so precious, whose every moment deprives me from so many Pleasures with which I should be ravish'd.</hi> These Expressions being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with little Amorous Actions, that spoke yet more, and what was to follow, you may imagine with what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience the Prince was seiz'd. <hi>I have heard, I have seen enough,</hi> said he to the Woman, <hi>to distract a Person far more Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient than I am, though I have had but too much with this ungrateful Woman that has so basely abused me. I will immediately rush in upon them.</hi> He upon that left the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:204247:76"/> and went towards the Chamber-Door, where with over-earnestness in the dark fumbling for the Lock, he made so much noise, as gave them notice some Body was near; that made <hi>Francelia</hi> to endeavour getting off of the Bed, where she was with <hi>Sancti Pater,</hi> but one of her Feet being intangled in her Coats, she was found by the Prince in that posture, and the <hi>Sancti Pater</hi> lying still on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side of the Bed, who so soon as he had perceived the Prince, got off, and while he was venting his Passion against <hi>Francelia,</hi> sneaked away.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you what the Prince's Passion suggested him to say; it suffices that I tell you he wanted words to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press his Resentments; wherefore I may very well fail in the same Nature; but at his going away he told her, that he would soon rid himself of those Troubles, and her of her Ruffian; and with that stepping to the Table he took along with him all the Papers that were on it, and tore them all along as he went out of the Chamber; he retir'd afterwards to his Lodgings, where how he spent that night any abused Lover may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francelia</hi> mean time left alone in such a Confusion, as can scarce be imagined,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:204247:77"/> was a long time e're she could recover her self, and when she did, 'twas with so much remaining disorder, that she could not find any way of making any excuse for a thing, which had been but too visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Prince. She found that there was requir'd a greater Calm, than she could yet be Mistress of in her Mind, to digest well this business, and to frame the least appearance of excuse or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; she therefore abandon'd her self to Tears, and in the excess of her Grief, she at last sell into a Slumber, which contributed much to recollect her Mind, and to bring her again into some kind of frame; but the more she thought on some excuse, the more she found it diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to make one; and all she could build upon, was in laying all the fault on the <hi>Sancti Pater</hi>'s Insolencies, and making him guilty of attempting to have gain'd by force, what she would not freely yield to him: Because she had no other shift, she was glad to make use of that, till she had an opportunity to speak to the Prince, so as that he might with patience hear out her whole Story: She sufficiently School'd her Woman, and tax'd her with perfidiousness; she on the other Hand, who wholly rely'd on the Prince's Promises and Favours, unwilling to have
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:204247:77"/> a continual noise about her Ears, fairly pack'd up her Tools and march'd off. <hi>Francelia</hi> on the other hand failed not to send a private Message to her disappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Lover, to let him know what she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd to do, and say to the Prince, that he might provide against that Storm, which was unavoidably to fall upon him; she also acquainted him with what the Prince had said and done in his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, after he was got away; and how he had torn in pieces part of those Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers that were left upon the Table, and had carried the rest of them away with him.</p>
            <p>The Prince mean time on his part was not wanting, he had sent a Message to <hi>Sancti Pater,</hi> to command him to leave his Dominions, and to immediately go for <hi>France.</hi> That had somewhat surpriz'd him, and though he could not but know he deserv'd a far more severe Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and much more of Rigour shew'd him; yet such was his Love and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment to that Woman, that he could not conclude on obeying the Prince's Orders: Yet he was so cunning, as to feign, as if he would forthwith submit to them, but that was to get time only, and to have Conference about the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness with <hi>Francelia,</hi> how to manage things
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:204247:78"/> under pretence of taking his Leave of her, in the presence of other Persons; but underhand he consulted divers Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, what should be done in such a Case, whether he was to obey the Prince, or not, so long as he was invested with the Character of a publick Minister of State. Some were for his immediate returning to <hi>France;</hi> others more affected to the <hi>French</hi> Interest, would have him to stay, to dispute the business with the Prince, and to beard him in his own Palace, to the Honour of him, whose Pentioners they were, and to the discredit of that good Prince, whose Subjects they were on the outside only. Upon this <hi>Sancti Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> did adventure to tarry here for some time, notwithstanding the Prince's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press Orders to the contrary; and here he remained in opposition to the Prince's Will and Pleasure, for a considerable time, till he was told, that it was not safe for him to tarry here; that he was best to make haste to be gone, lest worse should befall him. That Advice did make him look about him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude upon leaving the Land and his dear Mistress behind him, which in a little time after he did.</p>
            <p>During his stay here, after the Prince had made that Discovery, and for some
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:204247:78"/> time after, <hi>Francelia</hi> endeavour'd to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade the Prince of her Innocence, and that <hi>Sancti Pater</hi> was only guilty: But he had heard and seen too much, to let that pass; and he had observ'd, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that she had express'd much more of forwardness than he; wherefore the Prince was a long while before he would be reconciled to his Faithless Mistress; yet, at last, his good Nature prevail'd over his Resentments, and upon her hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble submission, and acknowledging of her Error, he again received her into Favour. Some say, that amongst those Papers which the Prince found upon the Table, he had the good Fortune to tare in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the most Satyrical Piece against him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self that any <hi>French</hi> Pen could write, whetted on with all the Malice and Scorn imaginable: Those other Papers which he took away with him being indifferent things, he flung them into the Fire. <hi>Francelia</hi>'s peace once again made with the Prince, she soon got again the same ascendant over his Mind, as she had been Mistress of before, and if it was possible she Captivated him more than ever; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somuch, that at last, his whole delight was to walk a little, and then to spend the rest of his time with her in her Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It was there, that a little before he
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:204247:79"/> fell ill of his last fit of Sickness, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into her Chamber, and finding fault with some odd kind of smell, which did offend him, she treated him with some excellent Cordial, which she said, she had newly received from <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> but the Prince did very much dislike the taste of it, and divers times found fault with it that night; however, he retired Indispos'd, and never held up his Head after that; divers Persons spent their Judgments upon it, as their Passions, or Interests did lead them; but the poor Prince fell into Fits of Convulsions and Apoplexy, in which Fits having had some Intervals, he recommended <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celia</hi> and <hi>Helanda</hi> to his Brothers Care; thus expressing his Love towards her to the last day of his Life.</p>
            <p>So soon as the Prince was taken ill, she made strict Inquiries of his Physici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Whether there was any danger? and when she was advertis'd, that he was threatned with Death, she began to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for a Retreat: she presently put up all her Jewels, and all the Gold she had, made away the best part of her Goods; and all that she could not conveniently send away into <hi>France,</hi> she put into trusty Hands here; after which, she stay'd here so long as she could conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:204247:79"/> to indeavour to get some Arears due to her, being very unwilling to leave any thing behind her, but what she could not take along with her. It is reported, That since her return to <hi>France,</hi> she has had Addresses made by divers persons; but amongst the rest, she fancy'd one of good Meen, who pretended to be most passionately in Love; but in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, it prov'd to be more with her Gold, than with her Person; for understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how forward she was at playing at Cards, he made himself of the same Humour, and brought with him, one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, three or four more nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gamsters, who play'd as genteely, lost their Monies as unconcern'd at first, and were as free and liberal to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, as any persons in the World could be; insomuch, that <hi>Francelia</hi> was very well satisfy'd with their agreeable Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, and she particularly expres'd to her pretended Lover, the Resentments she had for his Care, in providing for her such excellent Company; but in the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, by her continuance at Play, they, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with her Gallant, made a shift to win about some twenty thousand Pounds from her; after which, the Gallants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew themselves little by little from her House, and at last, the Gallant also did
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:204247:80"/> on the sudden disappear, and was never heard of since. Some say, that they were a knot of Officers, that wanted so much Money to make their Equipage for this Campaign in <hi>Alsatia;</hi> where they now Swagger, and spend as high as the best, at the Cost and Charge of <hi>Francelia.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:80"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A True Relation of the Cruelties and Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the <hi>French,</hi> upon the <hi>English</hi> Prisoners of War. Being a Journal of their Travels from <hi>Dinan</hi> in <hi>Britany,</hi> to <hi>Thoulon</hi> in <hi>Provence;</hi> and back again. With a Description of the Scituation, and Fortifications of all the Eminent Towns upon the Road, and their Distance. Of their Prisons and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spitals, and the Number of Men that died under their Cruelty; With the Names of many of them, and the Places of their Deaths and Burials: With an Aceount of the great Charity and Sufferings of the poor Protestants of <hi>France;</hi> And other mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Things that hapned upon the Way.</p>
            <p>The Memoirs of Monsieur <hi>Deageant;</hi> containing the most secret Transactions and Affairs, from the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. till the beginning of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry of the Cardinal <hi>de Richlieu.</hi> To which is added, a particular Relation of the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Embrun</hi>'s Voyage into <hi>England,</hi> and of his Negotiation for the Advancement of the Roman-Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion here; together with the Duke of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's</hi> Letters to the said Arch-Bishop, about the Progress of that Affair; which hapned the last Years of King <hi>James</hi> I. his Reign. Faithfully translated out of the <hi>French</hi> Original.</p>
            <p>The Cabinet Open'd; or, The Secret History of the Amours of Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> King. Translated from the <hi>French</hi> Copy.</p>
            <p>The History of the most Illustrious <hi>William</hi> P. of <hi>Orange;</hi> Deduc'd from the first Founders of the Ancient House of <hi>Nassau;</hi> together with the most considerable Actions of this present Prince. The second Edition.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:81"/>
            <p>A Collection of Fourteen Papers, relating to the Affairs of Church and State, in the Reign of the late King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Character of a Trimmer. His Opinion of, I. The Laws and Government. II. The Protestant Religion. III. The Papists. IV. Foreign Affairs. By the Honourable Sir <hi>William Coventry.</hi> The third Edition, carefully Corrected, and cleared from the Errors of the first Impression.</p>
            <p>An Impartial Relation of the Illegal Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings against St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> Colledg in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1687. Containing only Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact as they occurred. The Second Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To which is added the most Remarkable Passages omitted in the former. Collected by a Fellow of the said Colledg.</p>
            <p>The Absolute Necessity of standing vigorously by the present Government; or, A view of what both Church-men and Dissenters must expect, if by their unhappy Divisions, Popery and Tyranny should return again.</p>
            <p>The Justice of the Parliament, in inflicting of Punishments subsequent to Offenders, vindicated; and the Lawfulness of the present Government asserted.</p>
            <p>An Account of Mr. <hi>Perkinson</hi>'s Expulsion from the University of <hi>Oxfhrd,</hi> in late Times; in vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him from the false Aspersions cast upon him, in a late Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>The History of Passive Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Way to Peace among all Protestants; being a Letter of Reconciliation, sent by Bp. <hi>Ridley,</hi> to Bp. <hi>Hooper.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Sam. Johnson.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Purgatory prov'd by Miracles; collected out of <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> Authors. With some Remarkable Histories relating to <hi>Brittish, English,</hi> and <hi>Irish</hi> Saints. With a Preface concerning their Miracles. By Mr. <hi>Sam. Johnson.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:81"/>
            <p>A Seasonable Discourse, shewing the unreasonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Mischiefs of Imposition in Matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; Recommended to a serious Consideration. By Mr. <hi>Andr: Marvel,</hi> late Member of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Revolter.</hi> A Tragi-Comedy, acted between the <hi>Hind</hi> and <hi>Panther,</hi> and <hi>Religio Laici.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Poems, Satyrs, and Songs, against Popery and Tyranny. In four Parts. Most of them writ by the late Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Andrew Marvel,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Aylof,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stephen Colledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Answer to the Bp. of <hi>Rochester</hi>'s first and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Intrigues of the <hi>French</hi> King at <hi>Constantinople</hi> to imbroil <hi>Christendom;</hi> discover'd in several Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches past between him and the late Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, Grand Vizier, and Count <hi>Teckley;</hi> all of them found among that Count's Papers. With some Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plain English.</hi> In relation to the Real and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Friends to the <hi>English</hi> Monarchy. Humbly offer'd to the Consideration of his Majesty, and his Great Council, the Lords and Commons in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> Assembled. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi> With a short <hi>Preface,</hi> and an <hi>Appendix,</hi> concerning the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Oath administred to K. <hi>James</hi> II.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The New Nonconformist.</hi> Or, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Case in preaching after a Deprivation, incurr'd by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press words of a Statute; Fairly Stated and Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. With some short Reflections upon Mr. <hi>Cook</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. 1690. which was Licens'd by the Arch-Bishop's Chaplain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fate of France.</hi> A Discourse where it is shew'd, That by the <hi>Happy Revolution</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs of the <hi>French</hi> King for the <hi>Ʋniversal Monarchy</hi> are disappointed; and the Rational Grounds to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his Downfal near. In three Dialogues betwixt Father <hi>Petre,</hi> Father <hi>La Chaise,</hi> and two <hi>Protestant</hi> Gentlemen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:82"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Anatomy of a Jacobite Tory.</hi> In a Dialogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory,</hi> occasioned by the Act for Recognizing K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Great Bastard, Protector of the Little One.</hi> Done out of <hi>French.</hi> And for which the <hi>French</hi> King put forth a <hi>Proclamation,</hi> with a Reward of five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand <hi>Louis d'Ors,</hi> to discover the Author.</p>
            <p>A true Narrative of the Murders, Cruelties and Oppressions, perpetrated on the <hi>Protestants</hi> in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by the late K. <hi>James</hi>'s Agents, since his Arrival there. Published for the Information of the <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites,</hi> that endeavour his Return again.</p>
            <p>Reflection upon a Form of <hi>Prayer,</hi> lately set forth by the <hi>Jacobites</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and of an Abhorrence, rendred by the late King, to some of our Dissenting Bishops, upon his present Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's Landing.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preach'd before the High Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> on <hi>Sunday, April</hi> 27. 1690. And published by their special Command. By <hi>Geo. Meldrum,</hi> a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Minister, and till of late one of the Episcopal Clergy of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>A true Account of a late horrid Conspiracy to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray <hi>Holland</hi> to the <hi>French.</hi> And of the Trial, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, Condemnation and Execution of <hi>Jacob Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet,</hi> Sheriff of the Town of <hi>Sluys;</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Reolands,</hi> Master of the Ship call'd the <hi>Argle</hi> of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterdam,</hi> who were Executed for the said Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, <hi>May</hi> 6. 1690.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Essex</hi>'s Innocency and Honour vindicated; Or, <hi>Murther, Subornation, Perjury,</hi> and <hi>Oppression,</hi> justly charg'd on the Murderers of that Noble Lord, and True Patriot, <hi>Arthur</hi> (late) Earl of <hi>Essex.</hi> As prov'd before the Right Honourable (late) Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Lords, <hi>are ready to be Deposed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204247:82"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>